<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diatelesma. The fifth part or number comprehending the principall actions of Germany, France, Spaine, and the Neatherlands, continued from November, 1637.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4293.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107115</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22830202</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22830202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1789:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diatelesma. The fifth part or number comprehending the principall actions of Germany, France, Spaine, and the Neatherlands, continued from November, 1637.</title>
                  <author>N. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>189, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper, for Nath. Butter and Nich. Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to N.C. by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-P⁴ Q² (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DIATELESMA:</hi> THE FIFTH PART OR NVMBER. Comprehending THE PRINCIPALL ACTIONS OF GERMANY, FRANCE, SPAINE, AND The NEATHERLANDS.</p>
            <p>Continued from November, 1637.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — <bibl>Hom. Odyſſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Hic libere utere, &amp; fruere.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Harper,</hi> for <hi>Nath: Butter</hi> and <hi>Nich: Bourne.</hi> 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:2"/>
            <head>TO THE INGENVOVS READER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Claudere quae Coenas Lactuea ſolebat Auorum,</l>
                  <l>Dic mihi cur noſtras inchoat illa dapes?</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be queſtioned, why the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Neatherlands, vvhich uſed to ſtand in the Reare, ſhould leade the Van, in this diſcovery; It is here, as in a ranged Battell, Faces about, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not either Files or Ranks, but the Poſture onely: and it firſt preſented it ſelfe to my Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, was firſt brought downe Methodically, and firſt came to the Preſſe. If it be a miſtake reprehenſible, it was <hi>Error Protographi,</hi> and the Printer is not to be blamed. But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, in the diſpoſition of this Relation, by miſtaking the Title over-head, in the 3. Chap. and interrupting the Title of the Low-Dutch Story, by interweaving a New one, was <hi>Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Typographi,</hi> herein excuſable, that it was
<pb facs="tcp:25768:3"/>brought unto him by looſe ſheets, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, vvas vvilling to have ended it with the Tournament, more pleaſant than the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Warre: or elſe, as the beſt of Latine Poets doth ſometimes make a Breach in his Verſe, upon the Breach of a Speare; would ſhew his Fancie, in expreſsing the tumultuary Actions of Warre, by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of his Papers. However it hapned, he craveth your conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence at this Errour, and doubteth not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it from ſuch as you, who can more eaſily reduce the laſt ſheet of that Hiſtory to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, than he can recompoſe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:3"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Anſlaught upon <hi>Rhyneberke. Page 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaken upon good grounds. <hi>Page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Is proſecuted valiantly. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yet diſappointed happily. <hi>Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Spaniards ſurpriſed at <hi>Hanuit. Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Romaniſts baniſhed from <hi>Breda. Page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some perſons preſcribed by the Liegois. <hi>Page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Liegois require the Governour of <hi>Hoy</hi> to ſubmit and come in. <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Senate of <hi>Hoy</hi> returne their anſwer, and preſeribe the Liegois. <hi>Page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The order taken by the Liegois, to defend their Country againſt the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards. <hi>Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cardinall <hi>Infants</hi> preparation for Warre. <hi>Page 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Tournament intended at the <hi>Hage,</hi> at the Marriage of the Counteſſe of <hi>Solmes. Page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cavaliers divide themſelves into parties. <hi>Page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Batavians ſend out the Challenge. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And are anſwered by ſix Mauritanians. <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, by five Teutons. <hi>Page 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, by the Knights of <hi>Rome. Page 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, by the Knight of the <hi>Teares. Page 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifthly, the Chimiſts Reply to the Batavians Challenge. <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The entry of the Challengers. <hi>Page 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their devices. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The entry of the Mauritanian Knights. <hi>Page 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their devices. <hi>Page 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The entry of the Teuton Knights. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The entry of the Roman Knights. <hi>Page 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their devices. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The entry of the Knight <hi>de Larnes. Page 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The iſſue of the Tournament. <hi>Page 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seckinguen</hi> ſurpriſed by Duke <hi>Bernhard. Page 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Waldſhut</hi> ſurrendred to Him. <hi>Page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John de Werth</hi> ſent to <hi>Benfieldt. Page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Bryſſackers ſent to reſcue him upon the way. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Are utterly defeated by <hi>Cullembach. Page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John de Werth</hi> deſires to be exchanged for <hi>Horne. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25768:4"/>
                  <hi>Rhinefelden</hi> rebeſieged and ſurrendred. <hi>Page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Articles. <hi>Page 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Dukes proceedings. <hi>Page 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Treaſon at <hi>Maſtricht. Page 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcovered. <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And the Traitors executed. <hi>Page 65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Abbey of <hi>Beff</hi> plundered by the Viſcount <hi>Turenne. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Count <hi>William Naſſaw</hi> at the <hi>Blocker-dyke. Page 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Is aſſaulted by the Cardinall <hi>Infant. Page 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And forced to flye. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The conſequents of this Victorie. <hi>Page 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Caſtles of Saint <hi>Paul. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Martin de Freſne. Perne. Page 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therovenne,</hi> and other Forts and Abbeys taken by the French. <hi>Page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Siege of Saint <hi>Omaers. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The deſcription of Saint <hi>Omaers. Page 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The order of the Siege. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A French Captaine of horſe ſurpriſed by <hi>Forgatz. Page 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Forgatz</hi> defeated. <hi>Page 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Omaers</hi> ſuccoured by Prince <hi>Thomaſo. Page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Omaers</hi> relieved by <hi>Piccolomini. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Siege is raiſed. <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Siege and taking of <hi>Freyburg. Page 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A worthy Adventure of two Engliſh Gentlemen, but unfortunate. <hi>Page 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Towne ſurrendred. <hi>Page 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Five Regiments of <hi>Butlers Infantry</hi> defeated by <hi>Kanoftky. Page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>120</hi> Curriaſſiers ſurpriſed by <hi>Tupadell. Page 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>200</hi> Crabats and <hi>6</hi> Companies of Dragons ſlain and taken by <hi>Roſa. ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Altkirken</hi> taken in. <hi>John de Werth</hi> removed into <hi>France. Page 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>400</hi> Crabats ſlaine and routed by Duke <hi>Bernhard. Page 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Dunkercks men of Warre, taken at <hi>Port du Paſſage. Page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Divers places taken by the Prince of <hi>Conde. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bechara</hi> ſummoned, and not yeelding. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Duke <hi>de S. Simon</hi> bath order to enforce it. <hi>Page 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>Encounters <hi>1200</hi> Spaniards. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Defeateth them. Burneth <hi>Bechara. Page 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3000</hi> Spaniards defeated neere <hi>Fontarabie. Page 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And <hi>2</hi> Spaniſh Ships ſunke. <hi>Page 95</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25768:4"/>
            <head>The Occurrences in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ortified Townes, though by the beſt Politicians they are thought unneceſſary in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and abſolute Monarchies, defended by nature from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of forraigne Princes, ſave only in the Frontiers, as thoſe Realmes, which are incloſed with unacceſſible Mountains, or ſurrounded by the Ocean, yet in <hi>Ariſtocraties,</hi> for preſervation of that ſtate in its firſt ſpecies, and Kingdomes open to the incurſions of neighbouring Princes, they are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requiſite for ornament, but the ſafety of the ſtate, thoſe defences ſtanding as Bulwarks againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie of ſtrangers, and ſometimes ſtopping the courſe of their deſignes, though the preſidiary ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and inhabitants be unprepared at their firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch to reſiſt them till both may arme, and make head againſt the violence of the aſſaylants; yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the art and induſtry of men to manage them, being otherwiſe eaſily aſſaylable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25768:5"/>
               <hi>Proſpera prudenter: A diſcreet moderation is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the ſmiles, as the frowns of fortune: to endure the laſt with a well governed patience, is the way to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh her: and to abide ſecure in confidence of perpetuall good ſucceſſe, is not ſeldome the cauſe of utter loſſe, often of jeopardy.</hi> The happy event of the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> his travels before <hi>Breda,</hi> had filled the hearts of the people under the Government of the united States, with joy; and the Catholike Kings Allyes with emulation; The loſſe of ſo important a place, was not eaſilier digeſted, and the Spaniſh men of warre, expected an opportunity, to recover ſome thing which being added to their late prizes of <hi>Venloe</hi> and <hi>Ruremund,</hi> might counterpoyſe the loſſe at <hi>Breda; Octob.</hi> 16.26, was the day, which preſented the occaſion which was undertaken prudently, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted valiantly, and might have ended gloriouſly, had not the <hi>Epimethean</hi> wits of the Statiſh Garriſon been better then their <hi>Promethean.</hi> It was then a day of jollity at <hi>Rhinberck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Anſlaught upon <hi>Rhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berck.</hi>
               </note> (a little but ſtrong peece in the Frontiers of <hi>Gelderland</hi>) for joy of the Prince his late atchievment: the bonfires made the night ſeeme as glorious as day, the great Ordnance thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred out a Proclamation of triumphant victory, the ſouldiers and inhabitants kept Revels and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and as if there had been no enemy neer them, and after their feeding, lay downe to ſleepe. The Spaniſh Garriſons of <hi>Guelders, Gennep, Ruremund, Venlo,</hi> and other places upon the Maze, conjecturing what the iſſue of that dayes froliking might be, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered up 1500 men, and armed with Petards and ſuch like inſtruments, marched up thither-ward to ſurprize the City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25768:5"/>
Each circumſtance anſwered their hopes for execution of the Enterprize;
<note place="margin">Undertaken upon good grounds.</note> the Lord of <hi>Wynbergen</hi> was the perſon to whoſe care the cuſtody and government of the Towne was deputed. He was then abſent from his charge, and his abſence was no ſmall encouragement to the undertakers: <hi>Common men will aſſume more liberty, when their prime Commander is away, then they dare think of while he is with them:</hi> The darknes of the night concealed their approches, and the loud reports of the Canon, and out-ſtretched ſhouts of the people, their actions. An artificiall bridge, was laid over one part of the outward Moat, and a pile of bruſh-wood and bul-ruſhes dammed up an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; the Canons were ready to play, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to enter, yet nothing was ſuſpected, much leſſe perceived by the Garriſon and inhabitants. How happy a preſage was this of their wiſhed end? their counſels hitherto found no reluctancy, in a ſtill ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they ſtood armed to give the aſſault, till the triumphs being paſt, and as ſtill a ſilence in the Town, as was obſerved in the Army, gave the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylants ſome evidence, that then was their time for action. The word was given,
<note place="margin">Is proſecuted valiantly.</note> and each man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed himſelf to an active obedience. The aſſault was made with ſuch violence, that one of the gates, which was made only for the ingreſſe and egreſſe of friends, was therby become under the command of the enemies. Heere only was the rub which ſtayed the race of their conqueſt, the draw-bridge was up, and that being wanting ſtopt them in their full car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer. But it only hindred their ſpeed, and could not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25768:6"/>divert the reſolved <hi>Spaniards</hi> from proſecution of this (thus farre fortunate) beginning. <hi>True valour is not heartleſſe upon each diſadvantage, and a right ſouldier accounts it his honour to encounter with difficulties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the way was thus hedged up, yet on they went, but not with ſuch ſpeed as they intended, nor with that happineſſe, which their hopes had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The aſſault was diſcovered then by a Sentinell, whoſe fear made the danger greater then it was, his throat proclayming the ſtate of the Town to be paſt danger, as already in the abſolute power of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The Citizens ſtood like amazed men, and were ready to buy their lives, with the voluntary ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of their goods to the victor; only the Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Governours heart fainted not, hee made good uſe of the little breathing time, the yawne of the bridge had given him, beat up the Alarum, drew up his Companies together, and wiſely ordering his half diſtracted men, who by his example took freſh courage, fell upon the Enemy with an impetuous violence, when having ſcaled the walls, hee ganto cry <hi>victoria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The end crowneth the work:</hi>
               <note place="margin">And diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily.</note> had the concluſion bin anſwerable to the premiſes, the Governour of <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> the principall adventurer in this expedition had got much more profit, by the Cataſtrophe then glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by his well adviſed Enterprize. <hi>Weſell</hi> had bin blocked up, though no Enemy appeared in the field; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Garriſons had incircled it, nor could it have received relief from the States conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently. The valour and vigilance of the Lievtenant Governour prevented al with his new awaked men,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25768:6"/>he made an aſſault upon the over-watched adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; who neither prepared perfectly to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor offend the Garriſon (ſome of his men being upon the wal, and rather ſeeking the way down into the City, to endamage the defendants, then toſecure themſelves, others got over the Moat, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the aſſiſtance of their companions &amp; friends then affronts of their foes) and in concluſion, with the loſſe of his own life, and 60 of his men, repulſed the beſieger with the ſlaughter of ſome hundreds of his men, and many priſoners leaving the name of <hi>Wike</hi> (ſo was he called) more glorious after his death then it was in his life by dying victoriouſly.</p>
            <p>Yet nor his valour nor fate was all, to which the Town was obliged, for this deliverance. Some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accidents intercided, which forwarded, if not perfected it. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Canon was not good, two old Peeces were planted to ſcoure the ſtreets, when the Gate was laid open, and thoſe (craſie things) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt diſcharging, fell on pieces: and then, the noyſe of the Guns within the Town being heard at <hi>Weſell,</hi> not above four Engliſh miles thence diſtant, ſome companies were ſent out with 3 Drums, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt their confederates which according to direction beating the marches of 3 ſeverall Nations diſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from preſuming too far, as not knowing what Enemy might be behinde them, and ſo cauſed them to leave their weapons, to ſave their perſons, their Petards, Granadoes, Pikes, Halberts, Harquebuſſes, of crocks, and other military inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being thus made a prey to the victorious <hi>Hollander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25768:7"/>
               <hi>Stratagems in warre are like goodly houſes in eminent Cities,</hi> one is but the model of another. This deſigne of the Spaniſh garriſons was the pattern of the like to the Statiſts of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> againſt the little city of <hi>Hanuyit,</hi> which was undertaken as adviſedly as the other, and ended more happily, though not proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo eagerly.</p>
            <p>Their intentions were different, as their iſſues: theſe laſt adventurers had no deſigne upon the place, which deſired neutrality, but upon four com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Spaniſh foot and horſe, which were thruſt upon the city as Preſidiaries, whom the duke of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villon</hi> intended to ſurpriſe by onſlaught, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the city to its antient liberty. To this purpoſe the fifth of November new ſtile,
<note place="margin">Surpriſed at Hanuit.</note> withall the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and ſome fire-lockes drawne of each company in the garriſon, nine out of each companies, under two Captaines, three lievtenants and three enſignes, armed with petards and hand granadoes, hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched about eight at night towards the city, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in little <hi>Brabant</hi> upon the frontiers of the Biſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> and arrived there the next morning before day. His approach was ſuſpected by the ſentinell, but not knowne perfectly: the Watchman heard a noyſe, and called his Corporall, who comming from the Corps dugard, and liſtning a while in vain for a better information, (the army upon the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels word keeping ſtrict ſilence) returned, checking the ſcout for his vaine feare, which he concluded to have troubled his fancy with an ungrounded ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an approaching enemy. <hi>Facile credimus quod volumus, Mens underſtandings are often fooled by their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25768:7"/>corruptible appetite;</hi> which preſenting things to the ſence otherwiſe than they are, deludeth the reaſon, and by a falſe conception produceth a Phrygian Monſter, too late repentance. The departure and ſecurity of the corporall was not hid from the camp, which preſently ſcaled the walls, opened the gates, fell upon the weake corps du gard, of which they ſlew ſome, and tooke others priſoners, to the great amaſement of the ſoldiers, who for their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with Prieſts ranne into the church-yard, church and ſteeple. The church &amp; hallowed ground about it prooved a fanctuary to thoſe which had retyred thither, they deſired quarter and had it. But the ſteeple could not ſecure them within, the Prieſts unwilling to yeeld, jangled the bells as in a common combuſtion, hoping by that meanes to call in ſome of their neighbouring allyes to their ſuccour, and not depend upon their enemies mercy. But whileſt they thus flatter themſelves with help from abroad, death attends them from within, ten barrels of gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouder placed in the tower as in a ſtore-houſe (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſually or otherwiſe it is uncertaine) taking fire, and blowing up the prieſts and ſeventy others, which were fled thither with them.</p>
            <p>The next day the duke returned to <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> waited upon by an hundred and eighty ſoldiers pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, two and forty horſes and their equipage, one Antient, one cornet, and onely one Enſigne, the reſt being burned and loſt, but without any pillage from the citiſens, having commanded his ſoldiers by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that they ſhould re-deliver all they had taken from the inhabitants, into the hands of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25768:8"/>to be reſtored to the right owners, which they did accordingly, and the auditor performed it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>Newes of the good ſucceſſe of the States de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes had in <hi>Braſil,</hi> were brought about the ſame time into the Netherlands, the ſumme wherof was this, That the Hollanders got ground daily there, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the time that the Spaniard with twenty five ſouldiers having paſſed the river S. <hi>Franciſco,</hi> had taken ſome Hollanders priſoners, upon whom they ſet ſo high a ranſome, that each common man was valued at three hundred gilders, and each Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at a thouſand.</p>
            <p>That they expected every day a good account from thoſe nine men of Warre, the <hi>Amersfort,</hi> the <hi>Neptune,</hi> the <hi>golden Sunne,</hi> the <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> the <hi>Gray Wife,</hi> the Pinnace <hi>Sperrhewer,</hi> the Pinnace <hi>Fernam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucke, Endract,</hi> and the <hi>Halfe-Moon,</hi> which they had ſent with eight hundred ſouldiers under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Kein</hi> the Captaine of the Guard, and foure hundred mariners under Captaine <hi>Iohn Wendel,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the caſtle of <hi>Myne,</hi> with aſſurance that they had taken it.</p>
            <p>That the ſhip called the <hi>Weſell,</hi> ſayling towards the Weſt Indies, about twenty one degrees of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne latitude had taken a Spaniſh-veſſel laden with two hundred and forty cheſts of ſugar, and ſent it to <hi>Pariba.</hi> That the <hi>Creſcent</hi> had brought from <hi>Guinee</hi> a hundred ſeventy eight Negroes, which were ſould for 258000 Ryals of eight, that is, each man at one hundred and ten French Crownes, a price ſet upon them for their ſervice in the ſugar Mills, wherein
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25768:8"/>they expect not any other worth, that being the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple trade of the countrey. That their ordinary traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique was highly improved, both in general by the way of policie, their Ferries, weights, and Offices, being ſet at an high rate: and in particular, a ſtrange encreaſe of trade. All which jointly were no ſmall encouragement to the Commons: but that which rejoyced them moſt, was to be eye witneſſes of a prize taken by their ſea Captaine <hi>Cornelius Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Ioll,</hi> who the very day that theſe novels were brought to the States, brought into the Texel fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene thouſand pounds ſterling, taken from the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fleet; and left his confederate Captaine <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Michael Roſendale</hi> tugging for another, of whoſe ſucceſſe he gave them ſome probable evidence.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Pax una triumphis</l>
               <l>Innumeris potior: —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Halfe a loafe with quiet is better than a table ſtuffed with variety of diſhes, where <hi>Ate</hi> ſits as miſtreſſe of the feaſt, and brawles bring up the ſervices. The people tooke ſome pleaſure in hearing of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe abroad, by the means of their ſouldiery: yet were more inquiſitive after ſome neerer negotiation at home: a treaty (as it was ſuppoſed of peace) begun at <hi>Roſendale,</hi> betwixt the Deputies of the Cardinall Infant and the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> But the end an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not their expectation, the Treaty ended on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in concluding a ſet rate upon the ranſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of priſoners taken in the <hi>Betwe</hi> &amp; <hi>Velew,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at a moneths pay for a man, according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25768:9"/>ſtates, and particularly of the Governour of <hi>Geldres,</hi> who was taken at his laſt deſigne upon <hi>Rhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and ſo after two moneths deliberation, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley ended, and the deputies returned home.</p>
            <p>Winter now grew on, and the armies not able to keepe the field were deſigned to their garriſons and Winter quarters; the States ſouldiers being lodged in <hi>Breda,</hi> S. <hi>Hertogenboſch, Berghen-up-Zoom, Graves, Nimeghen,</hi> and the frontiers of <hi>Brabant,</hi> to preſerve the inward parts of that Ariſtocracy from invaſion by the Cardinall Infants forces. And thoſe Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh troups which were muſtered up about <hi>Antwerp, Lyer,</hi> and <hi>Mechlen,</hi> were garriſoned in the frontiers of <hi>Artois, Flanders</hi> and <hi>Henault,</hi> where we will leave them. Onely <hi>Piccolomini</hi> found ſome trouble before he could diſpoſe his army for Winter. The dioceſſe of <hi>Liege</hi> was firſt appointed for his reſidence. But the Luicklanders, who would not entertaine him, ſtood upon their gard, and kept him out, and in the end Gulick-land was forced to receive him, where how welcome hee was may be collected no leſſe by the oppoſition made by the duke of <hi>Neuburg</hi> againſt him, who firſt ſent his Agent to treat with him, and to perſwade him (if his oratorie could prevaile ſo much) to remove the Sceance of his forces, and to lay it elſewhere: and this courſe not prevailing, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the States of <hi>Berck</hi> and <hi>Gulicke,</hi> fortified <hi>Mulheim</hi> both by water and land, leſt the Italian Count ſhould attempt to inforce it. Then by the flight of the Natives and inhabitants of <hi>Sittert, Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren</hi> and other places of that dukedome, from their dwellings, upon the newes of his comming. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25768:9"/>with what difficulty he got his admittance might be gathered by his letters ſent to the Lords States of the United-Provinces, deſiring them not to oppoſe his neighbouring ſojournment, as ſuſpecting him for an enemy to their government, but to repute him as a Neutrall, that Imperiall army over which hee then commanded never being brought or imployed againſt them, but to the aid of the Spaniſh Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall againſt the Chriſtian King. Yet hee prevailed with the States for Neutrality, by the frequent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of his Agents, and with the duke of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> by his power, and about the beginning of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, his whole forces conſiſting of ſeven regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of horſe, and as many foot, though not halfe full, were brought and billeted in the <hi>Bercke, Gulicke,</hi> and <hi>Cleveland,</hi> under the commaunds of the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Major Generall <hi>Lamboy,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Suys,</hi> whileſt he in perſon went to <hi>Cologne</hi> to refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to conſult with the Elector there, about preparations againſt the Spring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It little availes to ſtuffe a City with numbers of men, if they have not the hearts to reſiſt a daring enemy. An handfull of ſouldiers armed with reſolution will doe more than a timorous multitude. Mulheim</hi> was ſufficiently provided for by the care of the Duke, who to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the city layd in an accrewt of 500 men; but expoſed to the pillage of the Imperialiſts, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe cowardiſe of thoſe to whom the keeping ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was committed, who yeelded upon the firſt ſight of the Roman Eagles, and had the reward of their falſehood and cowardiſe, beeing ſtript ſtarke naked and expelled by the Caeſareans, who immediately
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25768:10"/>began to plunder the city, and had utterly ſpoyled the Inhabitants, had not the Generall Major <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy</hi> expreſſely forbidden them to goe on ſo roughly againſt that people to whome they came for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in extremity, without any commiſſion to uſe them as enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Santen</hi> a ſmaller City, and not ſo ſtrongly guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſtood upon its liberty and maintained it. The Preſidiaries there were fewer in number than thoſe at <hi>Mulheim,</hi> yet of more valour and better fortune; they punctually denied to admit any part of the Caeſarean army to be billited there: and when <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colomini</hi> would have forced them to it, they took up their armes, ſtood upon their defence, and twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling thoſe troupes which came to compel them, made them ſeeke their winter ſtation elſewhere: and here the Polemicke occurrences betwixt the Prince Cardinal of Spaine, and the States of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces and Allyes have their period. Only about <hi>Artois</hi> and <hi>Henault</hi> ſomething was done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the cardinal of <hi>France</hi> and Infant of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Candale</hi> ſurpriſing the little city of <hi>Semay,</hi> three leagues from <hi>Avennes,</hi> November the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth or twenty ninth; and the Infant recovering it ſoone after, as alſo <hi>Beaumont,</hi> which in the Summer had bin taken by the French Forces, but was now regained by the Spaniard in Winter.</p>
            <p>Policy was now the object of all their ſtudies, preparation for war, reforming the regiments, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of juſtice, and other attendants of a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate, as marriages and triumphs, the cold breath of Winter giving ſome time of reſpit from military
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25768:10"/>actions &amp; a ſhort reſemblance of quiet. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to ſettle himſelfe in a ſure poſſeſſion of <hi>Breda,</hi> more fearing the practice of inteſtine then forraigne enemies firſt commanded all thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion to depart the City, and the order not prevailing, ſoon after effected it upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 15,
<note place="margin">The Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts baniſhed from <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </note> 25 (being Saint <hi>Katherines</hi> day) the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> which lurked in the City undiſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red intended a Maſſe in the Cloyſter of the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines,</hi> aſſembled together, and for feare of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion in the very act, barricadoed the doors, ſhut up all the windows and ſo fell to the ſervice. Their Counſell, and their act were both diſcovered to the Governour and Sheriffe of the place, who, in that nick of time, commanded a party of the Garriſon to attend them, marched to the Cloyſter, forc't o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the doores and windows, laid hands upon the Prieſt that ſung Maſſe, and by him diſcovering the reſt of that Religion, which lay ſecretly there, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed both him and them immediatly.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Liegois,</hi> though of the ſame profeſſion with the Elector of <hi>Collen,</hi> yet rather affected the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King,</hi> then him; and upon pretence of their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and revenge of the death of their late affected Governour <hi>Ruelle,</hi> publiſhed a Placard, <hi>December</hi> 7 17, againſt certaine ſpirituall, and civill perſons, whom they ſuſpected more to adhere to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Collen,</hi> then their State, the tenor wherof is as followeth.</p>
            <p>Upon the proofs given in Court of the number of the late Magiſtrate of this City, and about the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, conſpiracies, ſieges, blocking up, and other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25768:11"/>violent attempts againſt this City,
<note place="margin">Some perſons proſcribed by the <hi>Liegois.</hi>
               </note> and Territory; the Counſell hath condemned and judged as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Enemies to their native Country, the Lord <hi>de Iehen, de la Capelle, Godfrey de Bocholt, Horion de Heele,</hi> the Burgomaſter, <hi>Rauſin,</hi> the Sheriffs <hi>Dormael,</hi> and <hi>Zorne, Lambert Tournaco, Anthony de Marets, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt de Marets, Iohn de Henneff, Francis Bertrand</hi> the Major of <hi>Hoy, Kelenis</hi> the Quartermaſter, the Baron of <hi>Hollinghoven,</hi> the Lord Chancellour <hi>Blocquerie, Chockler</hi> and <hi>Proces</hi> both Canons of the Church of Saint <hi>Lambert,</hi> and Doctour <hi>Dawuns</hi> Paſtor of the 11000 Virgins; Promiſing: that if any of thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned perſons, can deliver his fellow, or any one of them, though hee were one of thoſe who had a hand in the murther of the Burgomaſter <hi>la Ruelle,</hi> he ſhall have beſides his particular pardon 200
<note n="*" place="margin">A <hi>Patacoon</hi> is a Royall of eighth, four ſhillings ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacoones</hi> for his guerdon: and if any of the Citizens can apprehend or kill any of the lay proſcribed men hee ſhall have 300 <hi>Patacoones;</hi> but, who ever can bring in one of the Spirituall perſons, hee ſhall have 500 <hi>Patacoons,</hi> and whoſoever can deliver up <hi>Iohn de Werth,</hi> or bring an authentike atteſtation that hee hath killed him, ſhall have for his recompence 1000 <hi>Patacoons:</hi> withall, prohibiting all and each perſon, to ſupport, mayntain, or lodge any of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed men, upon paine of ſuffering the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which is ſentenced upon them. Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>H. le Clercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they expreſſed their love to the memory of their late Magiſtrate, but their care in preſerving their franchiſes more. The name of a deceaſed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot yields a ſweet odor to the ſurvivors, but ſtands
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25768:11"/>in no equipage with the love that is juſtly challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from every Citizen by the Common-wealth. The Liegers declared both, though in a different meaſure, according to their ſeverall objects. <hi>Ruelle</hi> was reverenced for his care in preſerving the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtate; the ſtate, for it ſelfe, and the publike good of the Deniſons. The Placard was proclaimed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and two Prebends of Saint <hi>Lambert</hi> were preſently diſpatched to <hi>Hoy</hi> (a City upon the Maze 28 Engliſh miles Weſt, and by South from <hi>Liege</hi>) with authority to command the Governour there, to ſurrender up the place, into the hands of the <hi>Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;</hi> who without deliberation returned firſt,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Liegois</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Hoy</hi> to ſubmit and come in.</note> this doubtfull anſwer, that he would firſt be paid 25000 Gilders, which he was out of purſe, for maintenance of the Caſtle and Garriſon; and then a Categoricall deniall of the propoſition, adding that he was bound by oath to hold it for the Elector of <hi>Collen,</hi> and with that anſwer diſmiſſed them.</p>
            <p>All this was done by word of mouth; another courſe was followed, adviſed, and concluded of by the Governour, the Senate, and the Counſell of Warre <hi>Decemb.</hi> 17 27, and that was by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliation to return Placard for Placard, and proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, for proſcription; the Governour of <hi>Hoy,</hi> or <hi>Huy,</hi> being declared guilty of treaſon by the <hi>Leigois,</hi> the tenor wherof runneth thus.</p>
            <p>The Senate, and Counſell of Warre at <hi>Huy,</hi> who have taken a ſolemne Oath, to live and die in the Neutrality, which hitherto they have happily mayntained, cannot but wonder at the barbarous proceedings of the Senate, and Counſell of Warre
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25768:12"/>at <hi>Liege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Senate of <hi>Hoy</hi> returne their anſwer, and proſcribe the <hi>Liegois.</hi>
               </note> held there <hi>December</hi> the 7, 17. without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or reaſon, and concluded meerly out of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt all Humane and Divine Laws, the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Statutes of the Dioceſſe, and againſt the peace and power of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Archbiſhop E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Collen,</hi> to whom they owe obedience: not only by diſhonouring the preſent Governour with the falſe imputation of treaſon againſt his Country; but alſo by tyrannizing over the conſciences of their Chriſtian brethren, by continuing their inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and curſed bloud-ſhedding, and expoſing the life of the now Commander at <hi>Hoy,</hi> to ſale for the prize of 300 <hi>Patacons:</hi> And now becauſe, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Law of Nature, nor Nations can give any ſecurity for the proſcribed perſons: it is reſolved to proceed againſt them by way of Retorſion. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after a ſolemne proteſtation before the whole World, of their unwillingneſſe to take this courſe, if any other meanes for their ſafety might happily be deviſed; they, the Governour, Senate, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Warre at <hi>Hoy,</hi> judge likewiſe all Colonels, Captains, Lievtenants, Ancients, and others of the Counſell of War, at <hi>Liege</hi> apprehenſible, and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of treaſon; and promiſed 200 <hi>Patacons</hi> for each of thoſe Colonels, 150 for each of thoſe Captains, and 100 for each of the reſt ſo apprehended, and brought in either alive or dead: Reſerving withall all other Retorſions for our uſe, if the Counſell of <hi>Liege</hi> do proſecute their late Placard, or invent any new one, pronouncing all thoſe which ſhall lodge, or receive any of the fore-mentioned, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men lyable to the ſentence pronounced againſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25768:12"/>them: and admoniſhing all good Patriots, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhers to their Native Country; to continue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to their Prince. Subſcribed</p>
            <p>By order of the Counſell of Warre at <hi>Hoy</hi> and a little lower.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Le Recht</hi> Secretary.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Condruſii Agrippinenſes</hi> or <hi>Luicklanders</hi> were divided; but the capitall City, which ſhould give the law to all the reſt, and the major part of the Province held out for the Chriſtian King, levied forces for his Majeſty, ſupplyed them with arms,
<note place="margin">The order ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>Liegois</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi>
               </note> &amp; neceſſaries; and the King again to confirme his ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with them, underſtanding the diſtraction of their ſtate, by his Agent <hi>Ian:</hi> 30 old ſtile, and letters ſigned by himſelf, offered the forces which were levied there for him, to their ſervice, promiſing to aſſiſt them with more if need required it, and to pay them out of his own Exchequer. It was a gracious offer, and worthy of ſo Royall a King; but the <hi>Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geois</hi> were not ſo diſtreſſed, they provided ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for their owne ſafety both by a Martiall and Politike way; <hi>Daniell de Rive</hi> a valiant, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Souldier was made Generall over 4000 men, whom they armed againſt all ſuch as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined would offer to infringe their liberties: and he performed his charge ſo well, by keeping a carefull, and ſtrong watch in the Countrey, and <hi>Hesbay,</hi> that he ſecured them from the private practices of the Malecontents, and publike injuries, which might
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25768:13"/>otherwiſe have been put upon by their profeſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: One thing ſtill remayned, which was to take order for the common Magazine of victuals, that the Natives might not want bread, and that the Chapiter of <hi>Liege,</hi> which pretends a dominion over the whole Province, provided for, by an Edict, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ianuary</hi> 17, 27, commanding all the Boors to threſh out their corn, and to bring it to the capitall City, where it ſhould be laid up in the publike Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and be delivered out at a certaine rate for the uſe of the people. And this order took ſo good effect, that the peaſants reſerving only ſo much as was neceſſary for their owne uſe, brought the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynder to the publike ſtorehouſe; whence, the ſeller was ſupplyed with mony, and the buyer with bread for his family.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall <hi>Infant</hi> at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> though not then imployed in Acts of warre, was buſie in preparing for it againſt the ſpring: and becauſe men and mony are principally required for ſuch expeditions,
<note place="margin">The Cardinal <hi>Infantae's</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for warre.</note> hee ſent to his brother the Catholike King for both; the King anſwered his deſire, and in a Fleet of 32 ſayles of ſhipping ſent him 45 tuns of gold (if the figures deceive me not) and 4000 freſh ſouldiers, all which arrived ſucceſſefully at <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> about the midſt of <hi>December</hi> where the gold is to be coyned, ſave one Frigate loaden with Salt, which ſtragling from the Fleet, fell into the hands of <hi>Swartk,</hi> a Statiſh man of War, who ſurprized it, and brought it into <hi>Zeland, Decemb.</hi> 7, 17.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:25768:13"/>
            <head>Occurrences in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAP. II.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He new yeare came in with a new dreſſe.
<note place="margin">A Tourna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intended at the <hi>Hage,</hi> at the marriage of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Solmes.</hi>
               </note> The rough habit of war was put off for a ſeaſon, and a ſolemne Tournament more uſuall in peace then in War was performed at the <hi>Hage,</hi> by ſome noble perſonages deſigned therunto. The occaſion was this <hi>Monſieur de Brederode,</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the States Artillery a man of ſo noble a houſe that the old Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> accounted him the only Gentleman in the United Provinces, was to marry with Madamoſelle the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſſe of <hi>Solmes</hi> ſiſter to the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange.</hi> And to honour theſe Nuptials, the gallantry of the <hi>Batavian</hi> Court to ſhew themſelues not meer Courtiers but Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, alſo did not content themſelves with bare Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, but reſolved to run at the Ring. And the Bride again to gratifie them, deſigned a rich jewell for him that could ofteneſt take it in three courſes. To make the action beare ſome forme with the bravery of old times, they divided themſelves into parties,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25768:14"/>one wherof ſtood as challengers, and the reſt as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants.
<note place="margin">The <hi>Cavalliers</hi> divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into parties.</note> The Challengers were five <hi>Batavian</hi> Knights, who under the diſguiſed names of <hi>Bator, Claſsicus, Arminius, Civilis,</hi> and <hi>Mandrubace,</hi> being indeed <hi>Monſieur de Bredode</hi> the Bridegroom, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>de Manſhaw, Monſieur de Verneul</hi> a Major of Horſe, the Baron <hi>de Vauſtar,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de Chart,</hi> publiſhed firſt a generall challenge in theſe words.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Batavian</hi> Knights having for 3 years ſpace given notice by their Heraulds,
<note place="margin">Five <hi>Batavians</hi> ſend out the Challenge.</note> whom they have ſent abroad to that end, to all the Knights of the World that <hi>Feb.</hi> 6, 16. 1638, they would keep an open Camp at the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> their ordinary Randeſvouz, where every Knight that would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn an anſwer to their Challenge might ſafely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and try with them at 3 courſes with the Lance or ſharp Sword, or what other arms they pleaſed with aſſurance that he got the victory, might ſafely carry away the prize that the Ladies of the Court had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to him which could winne it: Now finding that the renown of their valour knowne through all the World, hath ſtruck a terrour into the hearts of thoſe that would oppoſe them, to the end that the Ladies might no longer expect the event they have agreed that 3 courſes at the Ring, ſhall ſuffice, to give a teſtimony of their valour: though if any be ſo raſhly hardy as to adventure further they will fight to the laſt, aſſuring them that they cannot find a more glorious Tombe. And ten days afterward a more ſpeciall Challenge in theſe words.</p>
            <p>The valour, wiſdome, and admirable diſcipline of the Prince that commands the <hi>Batavian</hi> Knights, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25768:14"/>hitherto made them invincible, there being no part of the earth which the Sun looks upon, which hath not felt ſome effects of their proweſſe, protects them from any accuſation of preſumption or teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in that reſolution which they have taken to fight hand to hand againſt all <hi>Cavalliers</hi> which dare ſay that there are any Ladies more worthy to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored then thoſe that beautifie this Court, and that they can find any more fair and vertuous then theſe whom we reverence: And to make this truth the more known, they attend with more then impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the comming of thoſe which rather out of paſſion then truth dare ſpeak otherwiſe that by their Arms always juſt and victorious, they may make it known that it is as eaſie for them to vanquiſh as to adventure: Given at the <hi>Hage, Feb.</hi> 6, 16. 1638.</p>
            <p>The defendants divided themſelves into ſeverall parties. Firſt, ſix <hi>Mauritanian</hi> Knights appearing under that title and the faigned names of <hi>Almanſor, Tindarache, Abdelmelec, Zelmander, Abindarae,</hi> and <hi>Algazair,</hi> being indeed the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> his brother Prince <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Deuxſport,</hi> the <hi>Rhinegrave, Monſieur de Vpdam, Monſieur de Berring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Billingſley</hi> returned this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Mauritanian</hi> Knights to the <hi>Batavian,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">And are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered 1 by 6 <hi>Mauritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </note> Know yee that in a Land where your Acts are not known, the news of your ſtrange adventure is arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and your vanity hath made you known where your valour durſt never appear. And we are come at the day and place appointed being ready to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your temerity. We who are deſcended from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25768:15"/>thoſe whoſe leſſer exploits have gained the title from the bloud of the Nation of <hi>Rodamot:</hi> and in the ſame Camp which you have opened, your glory ſhall find a Tombe and ours a Crown. But ſeeing that the Ladies deſire no bloudy teſtimony of your fidelity we will content our ſelves with the victory of three courſes at the Ring, where our activity ſhall make them know that there is but one thing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their perfections, to wit, our valour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them. And becauſe we admire the courage and merits of your invincible Prince, we ſhal make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to him, that there is neither force, valour, nor martiall skill in the World, more fit or worthy to expedite his deſignes then that of <hi>Almanſor,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The next party of defendants were five preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Teuton</hi> Knights under the names of <hi>Naſva, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentorix, Induciomar, Cimber,</hi> and <hi>Aroviſtas,</hi> which were Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> brother to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Freezland, Reſoar</hi> a Captain of Horſe, <hi>Du Mey Hauten,</hi> and <hi>Marquet</hi> who thus replyed to the <hi>Batavians Cartell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Teuton</hi> Knights to the <hi>Batavians,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">by the five <hi>Tentons.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. It being made known by Proclamation to all Nations that in the Court of <hi>Holland</hi> in view of the moſt excellent Prince all Knights deſirous of glory are met to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the prize deſigned by the Ladies to him that ſhall appeare moſt valiant and active: wee who have bin trained in the bloudy feats of War, and for our worthy Exploits deſerue to be regiſtred in the Temple of Memory, with the merited ſirname of victorious; preſent our ſelues in equipage to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the conditions of your <hi>Cartell</hi> with ſuch valour
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25768:15"/>as the Prince ſhall approve to be more temerity for you to contend with us for this prize, then ſhame for us to refuſe, and that to your confuſion the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhal avow that we ſo far ſurpaſſe you in loyalty and activity, that you ſhall be forced to do homage to our valour, and ſhall have only this comfort that you are vanquiſhed by the beſt Knights of the Earth.</p>
            <p>The next was a party perſonating Knights of <hi>Rome</hi> under the names of <hi>Servius, Sabinus, Voranius,</hi> and <hi>Vitellius,</hi> but truly Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">by the Knights of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> the Count <hi>de Waldike, Chevalier de Vauſtar,</hi> and <hi>de Loge,</hi> who thus replyed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romane</hi> Knights to the <hi>Batavians. Batavian</hi> Knights, The honorable Tournament which you have proclaimed to mayntain the beauty of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whom ye love, ſhall be the field where we will triumph in the titles of activity and valour which you uſurpe unjuſtly, and claime from all others. The merits of her whom we adore ſhall ſerve to increaſe our courages, and her graces inforce your Ladies to ſubmit to her. We are come from the heart of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to make it appeare that as there is no valour under Heaven equall to ours, nor beauty comparable to that of our Goddeſſes. All thoſe proud Eſcripts which publiſh your preſumption cannot divert us from combating with you with our Launce in reſt and ſword in hand to the utmoſt in a liſted field as you dare. To this end the <hi>Mars</hi> of Princes (having always knowne us to be victorious <hi>Cavalliers</hi>) our <hi>Dictator</hi> who hath prooved us valiant Legionaries, condemnes your temerity in daring to defie us, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25768:16"/>pronounceth that as the <hi>Romans</hi> have by their ſword got the univerſall Monarchie, ſo there is no activity, proweſſe, or valour, which muſt not give place to that of <hi>Servius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The next was a ſingle man who preſented himſelf under the title of the Knight of the <hi>Teares,</hi>
               <note n="4" place="margin">by the Knight of the Teares.</note> and was <hi>Monſieur de Maurier</hi> a Gentleman ſerving the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who in ſome ſad <hi>Stanzaes</hi> having expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his grief to the Knights defendants, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> thus replyed.</p>
            <p>The Knight of the <hi>Teares</hi> forſaken of Love and Fortune, deſpairing to be regarded by the one who hath hood-winked her ſelf from ſeeing him, and not to be diſcovered by the other, becauſe ſhe hath tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her backe towards him: is reſolved to ſhew his courage where hee is perſwaded to finde moſt reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, either to terminate ſo miſerable a life as his own, or to continue it with honour: and knowing that there is not a place where proweſſe and valour are ſo common as in this Countrey where (by the magnanimity of the Prince) the miracles therof are ordinary; is tranſported hither where hee believes he ſhall finde the ſtrongeſt oppoſition, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent ought to obtain the more glory. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſodainly cleered at his arrivall in the preſence of ſuch a grand <hi>Heroe,</hi> and in the view of ſuch glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princeſſes which troubled with compaſſion of his miſeries will ſuffer him either to periſh gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or triumph bravely upon his deſtiny, and his ill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boding ſtars. This is that which hath moved him to oppoſe theſe gallants, who vaunt that they wil hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the beſt Knights of the world, and to be victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25768:16"/>over all the Sun ſhines on. His actions ſhall fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie their words, and make it appeare to all whom either curioſity or valour hath drawn hither that the Challengers (unworthy of their Maſter and their Ladies) rather deſerve for their vanity of the aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant then the felicity they now enjoy. He will enter into the Liſt where his enemy hath promiſed him a crowne by bringing him to the place where he may gain it being reſolved to maintaine that the beauty of his Lady is beyond compare, and that the cauſe of his affliction is more juſt then that of their joy.</p>
            <p>The laſt party was made up by <hi>Monſieur Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werd,</hi> the Count <hi>de Horne,</hi> the Baron <hi>de Pontaſier, Monomaker de Foſſe,</hi> and <hi>Moir</hi> who preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the habit of Chimicks or Mountebanks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the names of <hi>Fauſtus, Mondor, Don Ferrand de Matamorbe</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Sivill, Macollo,</hi> and <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guets,</hi> who to conceale themſelves firſt put out this Bill.</p>
            <p>There are arrived in the City five Doctours, the moſt experimented in the World, who thorough all the Country where they paſſed formerly have cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Death before them, and fortified the ſeate of health. The diſeaſes they will cure are done ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by them, though they be extraordinary in their own natures. You ſhall ſee here a little Catalogue, and as it were a ſcrowle of all the miracles they can do: Their medicines are beyond price, and this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not able to pay for the effects of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; nevertheleſſe not regarding their worth for your love they have ſet ſuch a price upon them as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25768:17"/>you may reach unto, and will aſke no mony of the ſick till they be perfectly recovered. Come Lords and Ladies to our houſes, and loſe no occaſion. Knowing that health cannot be recovered without pain.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The dropſie of the ſpirit otherwiſe called va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we will eaſily cure with the powder of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of which wee have brought good ſtore, knowing that this Countrey is ſubject to that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We cure the Melancholy with a yellow oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is neither of our compoſition nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and which is worſt, we have but little of it left.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Wee cannot radically cure the malady of love, but wee have excellent Anodynes to aſſwage the pain therof.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Lunaticks, Mad men, and Hypocondriakes we cure by putting their braines in our Alembikes, and repoſing them afterwards in their proper place, with a little of our Balme, and ſo they ſodainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their ſences.</p>
            <p n="5">5 For the Vertigo or ſwimming of the head we have no other ceremony than to open the <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> that ſo thoſe evill vapors may breath out; and after by ſprinkling it with the water of Patience, the malady is eaſily cured.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The women which complaine of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands diſability, muſt attend us at home, for though our common remedies ſhould not profit them they not returne from us unſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:25768:17"/>
7 Such as deſire to have children may eaſily obtaine them, if they will uſe our Balme, which is excellent and eaſie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Againſt the failing of the heart our water of
<note n="*" place="margin">The word is an <hi>aequivocum,</hi> and ſignifies Caſh, Mony, or <hi>Coſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſse</hi> doth miraculouſly.</p>
            <p n="9">9 If the diſeaſes of the eyes proceed from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy (as according to <hi>Avicen</hi> an infinite number of them doe) we can make an excellent Collyrie of <hi>Crocus martis,</hi> which will worke readily and rarely.</p>
            <p n="10">10 We have an excellent Balme againſt that pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching evill, which the antient Maſters of our Art, <hi>Theophraſtus Paracelſus, Rabbi Elemi,</hi> and others call want of money; but it is very dangerous to practiſe it, and more dangerous to produce it, and therefore we conceale it, and that the rather, becauſe we judge by all appearances, that becauſe this ſecret or a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not knowne in this Countrey, the Natives are more hardy and induſtrious.</p>
            <p n="11">11 We have alſo brought with us a Balme, with which the phyſitians of <hi>Rome</hi> long ſince would have cured <hi>Lucrece,</hi> if ſhe would have permitted them: but wee thinke wee ſhall make little uſe of it in this countrey, becauſe it is ſayd that the Damoſels here are ſo loving and willing, that they have long ſince baniſhed all force and violence.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe Gallants alluding to the windy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Mountebanks, firſt diſcouered themſelves, and afterwards ſent out this anſwer to the challenge of the Batavian Knights.</p>
            <p>We are they which cal blacke life, and who by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25768:18"/>the knowledge of the beſt ſecrets of nature,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Chymiſts</hi> reply to the <hi>Bataviant</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</note> renew youth, and reſtore that ſtrength which age might or hath abated. As to ſuch, the liſt which in this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like feſtivity is open to all the Knights in the world, might have beene juſtly kept ſhut: and truly if wee had no other quality than that of Chymiſts, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds ought not to admit us in till the end of the combat, to cure their wounded men. But wee are men of a more glorious condition, the fire of Love, more forcible than that of the Chymicall furnace, hath transformed us into other men, and by the view of the greateſt goddeſſe on the earth wee are become Cavalliers. This Metamorphoſis hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us not to endure that challenge which was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by vanity, and publiſhed by temerity; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents whereof are, That there are Suns in the world more illuſtrious than that which ſhines upon us. We therefore demaund to have the liſt opened, that we may make theſe Batavians know, that our practiſe of keeping others in life, hath not deprived us of that skill that may acquire us the honour and glory of this Tournament. And as the world doth already judge of our rare skill by the events, ſo our will is alſo that you Knights may deem of our valour by our victory intending nothing elſe then a confeſſion from your own mouthes, that the Ladies whom you reverence equall not her whom we adore: or if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſhee be ſet in that circle of beauties you ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow that ſhe alone is worthy of adoration, that your ſelves are unworthy to love her, and unfit to ſerve her both thoſe Offices properly appertayning to us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:25768:18"/>
All theſe were the <hi>Proſcaenia</hi> to the enſuing gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry.
<note place="margin">The entry of the challengers</note> Nor were the Challenge and ſeverall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers written more wittily then the Action was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with bravery. The day came and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into the Liſt was in this manner. Firſt came the Challengers, their Marſhall <hi>de Camp</hi> before them attended with ſix Laqueyes in Carnation and Blue, 15 Trumpeters with their Caſſocks and Banderols of the ſame colours laced over with ſilver lace: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them ten footmen in the ſame Livery with five lead horſes, every two leading a horſe betweene them: Then five Pages on horsbacke and five Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, the Pages carrying the Bucklers and Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the Eſquires the Launces of the Knights, who followed immediatly in a triumphant Chariot drawn by ſix Lions (the Arms of the houſe of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derode</hi>) attended with ten Lacquies more, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chariot (drawn by ſix white Unicorns, and followed by ten Hawboyes and Sackbots on foot with long Caſſocks of the ſame Livery with the reſt) wherin were Slaves and Muſick both Lutes &amp; Violins. Their devices were theſe.
<note place="margin">Their devices.</note> For <hi>Monſieur de Brederode</hi> a Cypher of his Miſtreſſe name and his own upon a ſilver Shield, and the word in Spaniſh, <hi>Antes muerto que mudado.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Verneul.</hi> A Hart wounded by the flames comming from two eyes, and the word in Spaniſh <hi>Chiero lo che me quema.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Chant,</hi> A Hart with a Creſcent in it, and the word in French, <hi>Pourtant tou iours le meſme.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur le Baron de Vauſtar,</hi> A Crocodile with a Dart in his mouth, and theſe words about it in the learned language, <hi>Mahal fyr algit Nabuth.</hi> For <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25768:19"/>le Viſcount de Manſhaw.</hi> Two hands joyned with ſprigs of Lawrell and Mirtle in them, and the word in Latine, <hi>Ex fide gloria ſurgit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to them entred the firſt party Defendants that perſonated the <hi>Mauritanian</hi> Knights in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipage,
<note place="margin">The entry of the <hi>Mauritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Knights.</note> Firſt, Sir <hi>Iames Sandelane</hi> their Field-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Colonell of a Scottiſh Regiment of Horſe, and ſix footmen with Bows, Arrows, Shields, and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps, clad all in a ſtriped Scottiſh ſtuffe like High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers. After him a Moore on horsback beating the Kettle-drum, then 18 Trumpets, then 12 Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys on foot, then 8 Pages two a piece for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and one a piece for the others, who carried the Shields, and ſix Eſquires who carried the Knights Launces. After theſe came the ſix Knights with 3 Lacquies a piece by them, &amp; 12 Lacquies following leading a horſe between every 2, after theſe a troup of Lanciers all upon white horſes with ſnaffles and little ſaddles <hi>al' Angloiſe.</hi> The Knights themſelves were all with gold or ſilver Turbants on their heads, Caſſocks of the ſame that came downe to their knees, and underneath a Pantaloon of black. At the wriſts, neck, and eares great ſtore of pearle, and their Caſſocks faſtened before with pearle or diamond buttons, and both they and their train with their faces painted blacke. All their traine were in black Pantaloones, to make them ſeeme as naked <hi>Moores,</hi> with a little apron of cloth of gold or ſilver to hide their privities, and all with Cimeters by their ſides. The Knights deviſes were theſe. For the Prince Elector a plain ſable Shield, with this Latine Motto in a Scedule appendant: <hi>Maculas non contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25768:19"/>ullas:</hi> and in his Bendroll a Lion in a toyle, with this word; <hi>Quâ potero.</hi> For Prince <hi>Robert,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their devices</note> a Sword and Speare and other Arms, with this French In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Heritage de Cadets.</hi> For the <hi>Rhinegrave</hi> an Oake with a branch ſtruck off by thunder: with this Latine Motto, <hi>Adhus</hi> Iovis <hi>Arbor.</hi> For <hi>Beringham</hi> a Sun in a black Shield, the word in Spaniſh, <hi>Nada Enſuſia ni Limpieſſa.</hi> For <hi>Vpdam,</hi> a Sunne and halfe Moon, and a wheele betwixt them, with this Motto; <hi>Tolle Imples,</hi> which was proper and ſignificant, hee ſuing for the government of <hi>Hueſdun,</hi> and a Whale being the Arms of that City. For Sir <hi>Thomas Billinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi> A plaine ſilver Shield with only this written croſſe it, in Latine. <hi>Fatum inſcribit Eliza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to them entred the ſecond party Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants that petſonated the <hi>Teuton</hi> Knights in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipage (their Camp-marſhall being <hi>Armanville;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The entry of the <hi>Teuton</hi> Knights.</note> brother to <hi>Monſieur de Beringham</hi>) They came all clad like one another in green Velvet coats <hi>a la Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> layed al over with gold lace, with five led hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, 15 Lacquies, 15 Trumpets, five Pages, five E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquires all in green and gold Liveries accordingly; their Marſhall <hi>de Camp</hi> being <hi>Armanville</hi> brother to <hi>Monſieur de Beringham.</hi> The Knights deviſes were theſe. For Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> A <hi>Cupid</hi> with a Ring in one hand, and a Bow in the other. The word in French, <hi>Lue et Lautre.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur Reſoar,</hi> a Fortune with a Ring in her hand, and a hand with a Launce in it taking the Ring. The word in French, <hi>En deſpit d'elle.</hi> For <hi>Du Mey,</hi> A Hart pierced with ſix Darts all headed with C the firſt letter of his Miſtreſſe name. The word in Latine, <hi>Sic ſic juvat ire
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25768:20"/>ſub umbras.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Hauten,</hi> An Eagle in the clouds amongſt Thunder and Lightning, with this Spaniſh Inſcription, <hi>Ni matarmi, ni Spantarmi.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Marquet,</hi> A Sunne in eclipſe, with this in French, <hi>I'en ſortiray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The foure Roman Knights came in the next file;
<note place="margin">The entry of the <hi>Roman</hi> Knights.</note> their order was thus, Upon their Camp-marſhall, <hi>Monſieur la Fountain</hi> were attendant four Trumpets, two Drums, a Flute, four Pages, and four Eſquires, all on foot, and foure Horſes led by foure footmen, clothed like the old Roman Legionaries, then the four Knights, each with a Lacquay by him attired <hi>a la Romaine,</hi> and a man on horſeback with a Standard bearing the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagles, and theſe foure letters <hi>S. P. Q. R.</hi> all which though they made up the ſmalleſt number, and had the leaſt train, were braveſt in their aſſumed habits, no other ſhape appearing ſo gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous on horſback as the old <hi>Roman</hi> dreſſe. Their deviſes were thus ſet forth. For Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw</hi> a green Palme with a ſtone upon it, and this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Motto, <hi>Premitur non opprimitur.</hi> For the Count of <hi>Waldeck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their devices.</note> a Torch half extinguiſhed; the word: <hi>Reddant ſuſpiria flammas.</hi> For the <hi>Chevalier de Vauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> an Hart with <hi>Cupid</hi> upon one ſide, and <hi>Mars</hi> on the other, the word <hi>Accendor utroque.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Loge:</hi> a Shield full of flames, the word, <hi>Surſum movebor, donec extinguor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art was not wanting to ſet out this Gallantry; hitherto the ſpectatours were raviſhed with ſuch pleaſure as might delight them; an object of ſadnes, though accoutred in the beſt trim, the wits of that Nation could attire him, came in next to qualifie the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25768:20"/>exceſſe of delight,
<note place="margin">The entry of the Knight, <hi>de Larmes.</hi>
               </note> which might ariſe from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer glorious ſpectaeles: The Knight <hi>de L'armes,</hi> or teares himſelfe, and retinew all in Sable, and black the evidence of a grieved ſoule; his two Trumpets clothed in the Robes of ſorrow, ſounded a <hi>Surdine,</hi> his two Pages, Eſquire and two Footmen which led his horſe, both by their looks, geſture, and dreſſe, ſeemed to have a feeling of his miſery; and himſelf to make the people better acquainted with his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows rode in a Chariot, formed like a Tombe driven by Fortune, attended with ſix Lacquayes habited like himſelf, and the reſt of his traine in black, with teares of ſilver, which like the deaw upon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hovered in drops upon it. His deviſe was: Foure great teares in a ſable Shield, the word in French, <hi>Mon Soleif ou des Larmes:</hi> and in his Bandrolle, a Deaths head, with this Inſcription: <hi>Mon pis eſt Mon Mieux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The concluſion was more comicall. Thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended victorious enemies of Death and his Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſickneſſe and ſorrow, entred the Liſt in this ranke. Their Avantguard conſiſted of ſix Lacquies clothed in carnation and ſilver, and two Pageants, one preſenting <hi>Charons</hi> boat filled with paſſengers, among which were <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> the two great Phyſicians, and the otherlike a Stage with a Mountebank, and his man acting and ſelling drugs, and two Buffones repreſenting <hi>Don Quixote,</hi> and his Quire <hi>Sancho Pancha:</hi> the Reare conſiſting of the Pages, Squires, Footmen, led horſes, &amp; ſix Knights, whoſe leader <hi>Beavervard</hi> rode upon a Dromedary,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25768:21"/>all being clothed fantaſtically like Mountebanks. Their deviſes were thus. For <hi>Monſieur de Beaverwert</hi> a Death with this in French. <hi>Ie la donne aux autres.</hi> For the Count of <hi>Horn.</hi> All inſtruments of inciſion in his Shield. The word in Latine, <hi>Seco mel ùs, quam ſano.</hi> For the Baron <hi>de Pontaſier,</hi> (who was dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed like a <hi>Don</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi>) an Alembick with this word in Spaniſh, <hi>Alli dame el fuego d'Amor.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur Major,</hi> a hand catching of Flyes. The word in French, <hi>Bienheureux quien echappe.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomaker.</hi> A Fortune preſenting a cup. The word in Spaniſh, <hi>Non ti ſidur.</hi> For <hi>Monſieur de Foſſe,</hi> A hand holding out a bowle of wine. The word in Latine, <hi>Bacchica pocula praeſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the preparation, their action and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes followed thus. The Challengers and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers repaired to one end of the Liſt, to make their courſe ſucceſſively according to the order which they obſerved at their entry.
<note place="margin">The iſſue of the Tourna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> All confuſion was avoyded, every man had his three courſes, but the prize of that day was carried away by <hi>de Lege,</hi> whoſe fortune was more aſſiſting to him then his art: though he was not unskilfull in managing his horſe and launce. A Sun-ſhine day never ſeems long, the inhabitants neere the Pole, are ſaid to expreſſe ſome griefe, when their long day of almoſt three months continuance is buried in its firſt ſhort darkneſſe, and that this gallantry ſo full of delight might not be too ſoon finiſhed, the moſt excellent Princeſſe the Counteſſe Dowager of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the illuſtrious and moſt high-borne Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:25768:21"/>her eldeſt daughter, and the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> give three other Rings to the honour of ſuch as could winne them, and prolonged the ſport for three days, two of which were wonne by <hi>Pontaſiere,</hi> and the third by <hi>Reſear.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:25768:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Relation of the late Battaile fought between Duke</hi> Bernhard Weymar (<hi>Generall of the</hi> Swediſh <hi>Forces</hi>) <hi>and</hi> Iohn D'VVerth, <hi>chief Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the</hi> Imperiall <hi>Forces,</hi> March 1638.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Uke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar,</hi> who had not unhappily imployed his forces about the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the laſt Summer and Autumne, in the extremitie of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, after he had victualled <hi>Enſiſheim, Angelſtein,</hi> and <hi>Pfefſinguen,</hi> and left 800 men to guard the Forts which he had built upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> with an intent rather to abandon them honorably, then maintain them deſperatly, they being not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defence;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25768:22"/>repaired to the Valley of <hi>Delſpery,</hi> or <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to refreſh his weary Army; where his active ſpirit would ſearce let him reſt, rowſed him again ſpeedily upon the report of the victorious proceedings of his Enemy, which made an advantagious the of his abſence.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Baron tell his owne ſtory; and let his enemies pardon him if they imagine, he doth it too gloriouſly; <hi>Modeſty is not a Souldiers, but a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ornament:</hi> and let the Orator ſpare him if hee doe it not Rhetorically, or ſmoothly; hee profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not Arts but Arms; &amp; could manage his ſword, better then handle his pen. Thus he expreſt himſelfe in a letter, Dated at <hi>Offenburgh, Novemb.</hi> 13, 3. and directed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wee ſhould rob him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> part of his glory; if (ſince hee hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken it) we permit him not to be his own Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.</p>
            <p>Moſt Revorend Father, and moſt gracious Elector and Lord, die. I cannot but withall ſubmiſſion certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Electorall Highneſſe, that aſſoone as I had received certain intelligence that the Duke of <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> was gone towards <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to take up his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quarter, and my ſelf was able but to ſit on horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, (though the wound I received in the laſt bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail be not yet proſectly recovered, the bullet ſtill lying in my body) I thought it requiſite to attempt and recover the bridge and ſconces which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had made over, and upon the banks of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> that ſo I might get a ſcoure hibernall ſtation for my forces.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:25768:23"/>
To this end, <hi>Octob.</hi> 31 new ſtile, I paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> at <hi>Briſack,</hi> with the <hi>Alinger</hi> Horſmen, a part of the foot forces, and certain peeces of Ordnance march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeedily day and night, with an intent to aſſault them both by water and land: <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1, I arrived there, and viewed the out-moſt Sconces, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments on the <hi>Burgundian</hi> ſide, where percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that expedition was required principally for execution, and that the foot forces by reaſon of the uncouth way, could not follow ſo faſt, as I deſired: I cauſed my life-guard to alight and aſſault the firſt bridge and Sconce on foot which they did ſo ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that they forced the defendants to flie and ſeek their ſafety elſwhere. This was our firſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize which though it ſucceeded happily, cleered not the way to our eaſie proceeding. The Enemy had thrown off the bridge, and ſo ſtopped the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage that we had no other way to regaine it then by demoliſhing the Sconcs and making uſe of the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to repaire it. This ſtay was no ſmall advantage to the Enemy who made uſe of his time, and threw off another long bridge which lay over the ſecond River, and took his <hi>Poſto</hi> there: yet this loſſe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the induſtry of the horſmen who again aſſaulted and took in the two Sconces upon the next River, and forced the Defendants to run away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed into the fourth Sconce, where they threw off a great part of that bridge too, and gave ſuch fierce fire upon us, that I was compelled to attend the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of my Musketiers and greal Guas, before I could attempt farther againſt them. At laſt they came and I planted them upon the banke of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25768:23"/>whence by playing continually upon the Iland and Scorce, they did much ſlaughter, though they did not break downe the bridge. Another Engine I had deviſed for that ſervice; and uſed it happily. Some old veſſels filled with powder and fire-balls I cauſed to be bought from <hi>Briſack,</hi> which being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried downe by the violence or the ſtrcame falling upon the Enemies artificiall bridge; tore it in ſunder, and ſo ſeparated the Iland from the <hi>Reull</hi> Sconce which lay on the other ſide. This was a hight-work. The enſuing day preſented mee with a new buſines, The Enemy had in the Iland two Sconces, and there I perceived him fortifying and endrenching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for his more ſafety: To prevent him I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the horſmen and Dragoons to paſſe through an arme of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and the foot forces by boats which I had prepared for that purpoſe to make over into the Iland and aſſault the fourth Sconce lying behinde the locond bridge, which they did faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeying my directions, and effectually not retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without the prize. The fifth Sconce lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the bridge of boats neer before the <hi>Reull</hi> loo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ee. It was well manned with 200 men, and to take it in I cauſed the Cannon to bee carried over the River, and came my ſelfe in perſon before it. The ſtrong preparation for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> being perceived by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, cauſed them to ſend out a Drum, and deſire a parley. I heard them but gave them this ſhort an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; that I would not yield them conditions, nor accept the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>eſſe they yielded upon diſcretion. My actions attended upon thy words. I preſently aſſaulted and maſtered it, forced the defendants to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25768:24"/>flie, a part whereof making towards the broken bridge of boats were takon priſoners, an other part chaſed into the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and drowned, and the laſt which ſought for ſhe lter among the buſhes upon the Iland became a prey to the ſouldiers, and were put to the ſword. Thus farre having gone fortunately on immediatly. I took out the foot-forces to aſſault the <hi>Reall</hi> Sconce which was guarded with 600 men, &amp; defended with four peeoes of Ordnance: and to ſpeed it the ſooner I planted my Cannon againſt it, and played upon it with that violence, that I made an aſſaultable breach in the wall, and prepared to aſſault it. But he or the beſieged hang out the white Flag, ſend but a Drum, and deſired to treat, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving no other anſwer, but that they ſhould yield upon diſcretion, or if they ſtood out to the laſt, they ſhould be all put to the ſword, they ſtraight ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mercy, and were thus ordered. The Officers I kept as priſoners, the common ſouldiers which were willing, I took into ſervice, and diſmiſſed with white ſlaves. Whilſt I thus laboured about taking in the forecamed Forts, the Sergeant Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Enkenfourt,</hi> who had the command on the other ſide of the River, took in all the outermoſt Sconces and Retrenchments there, and the Lievtenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>de Melli</hi> the <hi>Cappler</hi> Sconce, which was above the bridge in the midſt of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and was guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by 50 French ſouldiers, and put them ſo hard to it, that all except 12 which had quarter, were either ſlain or drowned. This I have clecred againe the River of <hi>Rhine,</hi> and I thought it my duty to certifie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25768:24"/>your Electorall Highneſſe therof punctually. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
            <p>Your Electorall Highneſſes humble and obedient ſervant</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn de Werth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A victorious Army goes on like a devouring fire, carries all before it, till it meet with oppoſitions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to quell it. The Imperiall Colonell <hi>Mettanich</hi> was commanded by his Generall to make an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaught upon the Sconce at <hi>Druſenheim,</hi> hee did it, and carried it, and after that took the Fort at <hi>Kurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenhowſen</hi> by compoſition, and laſtly, blocked up <hi>Strasburg,</hi> an Imperiall City upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> having ſo ordered it as declining all neutrality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> thought himſelfe now ſufficiently loaden with ſpoyles, and returned with triumph to the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Court at <hi>Munchin,</hi> where for the time he was entertained graciouſly, feaſted and honored, but was ſoon recalled back to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> a ſtorme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing in the Weſt, which like an <hi>Hericano</hi> threatned thoſe parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> unleſſe that hee himſelfe by his preſence ſhould diſſolue it. The Duke of <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> who in the ſhort time of his repoſe had well vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualled both his Army and the City of <hi>Strasburg</hi> out of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> his diſcipline having gained the love of thoſe <hi>Helvetians,</hi> and ſtudied the meanes to repaſſe the <hi>Rhine, Ianuary</hi> 18, 28. aroſe from his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25768:25"/>head Quarter at <hi>Delmont,</hi> and though the ſeaſoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued againſt him by his reſolute courage anſwred all the difficulties it could propound. His attendants were only ſome Gentlemen and choice men of his army with whom he marched the ſame day to <hi>Pfef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finguen,</hi> and thence to <hi>Ingleſten,</hi> which are the keyes and inlets of <hi>Lauffen</hi> and <hi>Delmont,</hi> where was the firſt Randeſvouz of his horſe and Infantry. Here he made ſome ſtay but a ſhort one, the time being only to inſtruct them for the order of their march, and himſelfe departing the night following, wandred with this retinue, and furniſhed with ſix wagons lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſcaling ladders, Petards, and other ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of War. The wayes were myry and ſcarce paſſable, yet with much hardneſſe hee reached the next morning at the point of day, an houres going below <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffenburgh</hi> point-blank, againſt which lies the town of <hi>Seckinguen,</hi> the <hi>Rhine</hi> only parting them. The Dukes intention was to paſſe the River ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but his ſouldiers being wearied by the roughnes of the way, and ſharpneſſe of the ſeaſon, found themſelves unable to handle their Armes, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed with cold, and this cauſed him to repoſe there one day, not ſo much to reſt their wearied bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as to recover their limbes, which time was not loſt, the Duke himſelfe getting in the interim two little veſſels, by which hee could at once tranſport eight men, and no more over the River.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſmall Bottomes, <hi>Ianuary</hi> 20, 30, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to the River about three quarters of an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh mile below <hi>Seckinguen,</hi> a place which the eye of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25768:25"/>the inhabitants of that City, could not reach unto by reaſon of the Woods and Mountains which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their proſpect that way.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seckinguen</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by duke <hi>Bernh.</hi>
               </note> The Citizens being thus hood-winked from diſcerning the Dukes pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, by this ſmall help at divers times 100 reſolved Gentlemen, furniſht with ladders, Petards, &amp; other neceſſaries, were ferried over to the other banke, with inſtructions to aſſault the Towne, and make themſelves maſters of the boates belonging to the City, and of one Fery, which the Burgeſſes ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Dukes deſigne, had haled to the ſhoare, &amp; placed it neeer the gates of the Town, as a Flanker to ſecure them. The enterprize was undertaken cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, and ſped happily, his highneſſe ſouldiers became Maſters of the Towne, and Boats, but the Ferry-boat being boared in ſundry places by the Towneſmen, to make it unſerviceable for the Duke in that attempt, detained them an houre and halfe, to repair it, that thereby, and by the other veſſels which they had ſurprized <hi>Roſa's</hi> Regiment, and ſome more foot-forces might be brought to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When one knot in a churliſh piece of timber is rent, the reſt cleave eaſily aſunder.</hi> The Saxon Duke having advanced but thus farre proſperouſly, with a little wheeling about,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lauffenburg</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaught.</note> aſſaulted and tooke in <hi>Lauffenburg</hi> the ſame night, the terrour and diſtraction of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſens as much ſpeeding his deſigne as his own dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and his mens reſolutions. Though his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tards had done their worke effectually, the aſſaulted might have held out and kept the city, if their feare had not deprived them of counſell, by burning and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25768:26"/>demoliſhing the bridge (a thing almoſt as feaſible as imaginable, it being built of wood) but their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightment extinguiſhed their reaſon, and in ſtead of oppoſition they fell to ſubmiſſion, cleared the way, and gave him admittance voluntarily.</p>
            <p>By this ſucceſſe, though the Baron <hi>de Werth</hi> had cut off his former,
<note place="margin">Waldtſhut ſurrendred to the duke of Weymar.</note> he regained a new paſſage over the river, and to take poſſeſſion of it, he without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay ſent the Count of <hi>Naſſau</hi> with his regiment over the bridge, to joyne with <hi>Roſa,</hi> and with their united forces layd ſiege to <hi>Waldtſhut,</hi> where the garriſon perceiving an army incamped, and a banke raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, ſurrendred preſently upon fair tearms, and ſo the Duke without blowes became Maſter of their forreſt and free townes, but under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet here was not the period of his fortunes: two companies of Imperiall horſe, which were ſent, though too late, to re-inforce the Preſidiaries in <hi>Lauffenburg,</hi> came in unhappily for themſelves, to inlarge his victories. They met him unexpectedly, and were no ſooner diſcovered than vanquiſhed, ſome being ſlaine, others captivated, and few eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping death or impriſonment; as were alſo a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of foot, which followed them, though with ſome difficulty, the place of fight giving the Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Infantery conveniency to fight advantagiouſly, &amp; opportunity to retyre more conveniently, though not ſecurely, in the end they were diſcomfited with ſome ſlaughter, and purſued almoſt to <hi>Briſack</hi> by the victors, which ſtrewed the way with dead corp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25768:26"/>and returned to the campe with about ſixty pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
            <p>It was an ingenious device of the old Romans, to ſet the temple of Fortitude in ſo direct a way to the Temple of Honour, that no man could come to the laſt but through the firſt; <hi>Glory</hi> is not gained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger. The Dukes next deſigne was upon a ſtrong city <hi>Rhinfelden.</hi> Here he found a ſtrong erre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancie, and by the iſſue added not few graines, but many maſſy weights to his former gotten glory. The Chriſtian King had ſent him money to pay his army, and that ſupply gave his men freſh ſpirits: but he wanted amunition, and ſo might ſeeme to want ability to go forward with this great deſigne. From <hi>Schaffehouſen</hi> hee expected what hee wanted, pouder, which was ſent him downe the <hi>Rhine,</hi> but ſtayed by the Romiſh Cantons at <hi>Coblen:</hi> yet hee proceeded in his courſe daringly, not deſperately, being certified that the city was ſick of the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie, by ſome intercepted letters which hee found in the hand of a meſſenger ſent from thence to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack,</hi> whom hee apprehended and hung in the ſight of the garriſon ſouldiers. Being alſo ſupplied from <hi>Benefeldt, Colmar,</hi> and other townes in the Alliance, and under the command of the French King: and now he raiſeth batteries, imployes his pioners to undermine it, ſpares no more paines to ſubdue it, than the city to defend it ſelfe. When having with ſome ſmall loſſe to his army got a good advantage upon the city, his mines and batteries having bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken an aſſailable gap in the walls, and hee preparing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25768:27"/>to aſſault it, his deſigne was thwarted by the report of a knowne enemy, an army of old ſouldiers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon his backe, under experienced leaders, <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> the Bavarian, the Duke <hi>de Savelly,</hi> the Auſtrian Generall, and the Generall Majors <hi>Sperr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hewther</hi> and <hi>Enkenfourdt.</hi> And this for the time cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to raiſe his ſiege to attend their arrivall.</p>
            <p>February the 18 or 28, the Saxon duke began his expedition by that day the Imperial army was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced into the Blacke forreſt, by the helpe of the Peaſants, who firſt informed the Generall <hi>de Werth</hi> of the Dukes actions, and after cut out his way tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the brambles and thicke under-woods with their Bills and hatchets, to haſten the march of him and his confederats forces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vna cademque manus vulnus opemque tulit:</hi> The ſame tongues which by their clamor drew the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarian army thither, reported their comming and place of reſidence in the campe, and mooved the Duke with ſix regiments of horſe, amounting in all to twelve hundred; and three hundred musketiers, and ſixe field pieces, to meet him in companie, and to adventure the fortune of a battell.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> under the command of <hi>Savelli,</hi> were placed in the right Wing, and the <hi>Bavarians</hi> led by <hi>Iohn de Werth,</hi> in the left of that Army. The Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> which was caſually come to the D, of <hi>Weymars</hi> Camp, and would make one in the fight, commanded the left, and Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> himſelfe, the right wing of his forces. And now the battels joyn, the field-peeces, play awhile at ſome diſtance, but the adverſaries in the end come neere together,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25768:27"/>and then the Muſquets and leſſer Guns vomited bullets like hall-ſtones mingled with fire upon their diſchargers Enemies. It had been too violent a fight to have continued, had not the careleſneſſe of the ſouldiers in the left wing of the Dukes army, which gave the firſt charge, given the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to renew the combat; <hi>Wolff</hi> the Imperiall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell which led the Avant-guard; was mortally wounded and taken priſoner, with ſome other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and eleven Cornets, by which the common ſouldiers, judging that the battell was ended, ſlackt their hands, and fell on pillaging to the advantage of the <hi>Caeſareans,</hi> which rallyed again, and joyned with the other part of the army, inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding tobe avenged of the Dukes left wing, as in part they were, breaking its Ranks, &amp; ſeizing of the D. of <hi>Rohan</hi> as their priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though he was preſently reſcued by a Major of the then <hi>Rhinegraves,</hi> now the Count of <hi>Naſſaws</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment. The <hi>Saxon</hi> Duke, whoſe vigilant eye was over his Army, and tooke notice of each loſſe and gain, perceiving where his Enemies preſſed hardeſt upon him, drew up his foot-forces, to make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; but the <hi>Imperialiſt,</hi> repulſed them too, and got from him four peeces of Cannon, and three Cornets. The Duke as ſcorning this check without delay, came in with his Cavallary, and charged the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> ſo furiouſly, that he brok their Ranks, and it came to pell mell, in an horrid confuſion upon both ſides. What ſlaughter might have followed this tumultuary combat, a ſouldier can judge by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and reaſon may informe us by the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, three of the Dukes Colonels, <hi>Schavelitzhi,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25768:28"/>Dannenberg,</hi> and <hi>Erdman,</hi> or <hi>Erlach,</hi> being thereby made priſoners of War, and carried into <hi>Rhinefel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and 150 of his men ſodainly ſlain, as were alſo 300 of the Enemies. But the night drew on, and both the Generals ſounded a Retreat, unwilling to ſtrike at randome, <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> taking his way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Rhinefelden,</hi> into which hee thruſt 300 freſh men to ſtrengthen the Garriſon, and Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> yet keeping the field, whence hee diſpatcht a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to the other ſide of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to his Campe there to riſe, and meet him neer <hi>Seckvingen, Feb.</hi> 19. <hi>March</hi> 1, where thoſe 4 Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Horſe, and five of <hi>Infantry,</hi> which lay on the Weſt ſide of the River, met him at the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
            <p>Some time was ſpent there by the Counſell of Warre, but not much, and ſome few houres to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh himſelf, but not many; for the next day, <hi>March</hi> 2 new ſtile, himſelfe marched with his Infantry and Artillery, along the River toward <hi>Rhinfelden,</hi> having ſent his Cavallary before under the command of <hi>Tupadell</hi> through the blacke Forreſt, and both of them met again the next morning by ſeven a clock neere <hi>Biken,</hi> the place deſigned for their common Randezvouz. Counſell and Diſcipline doe more then ſtrength: The Duke uſed all, he drew his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into a cloſe body to conceale its number, and therby amuſed the wary <hi>Bavarian,</hi> who being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed by his Scouts, tooke the whole number, but for a party, and as thinking the prey caught, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed them round with all his forces, preſuming that none ſhould eſcape. His order was thus, He pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25768:28"/>ſome choice men in a Spinny neere <hi>Rhinfelden,</hi> with three of thoſe peeces which hee had gotten in the former battell, himſelfe encamping with <hi>Wahls</hi> Regiment, in the Forreſt ſomewhat further off, whiles his Cavallary was ranged in an adjace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t field, giving order that at the ſignall, they ſhould all ariſe together, and joyntly ruſh in upon the <hi>Weymariſh;</hi> fearing leaſt otherwiſe they might attempt to ſave themſelves by flight, upon the view of his whole Army. The Duke had his deſire, by his Enemies preparation againſt him, ſuffered him to come on, not diſcovering his ſtrength, till one part of the <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareans</hi> which appeared upon their march, the reſt being laid in a ditch, to conceale them, came within 100 paces of them, when ſodainly the Duke unlock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his cloſe body, appeared in his true proportion, diſcharged his Cannon croſſe-ways thrice, amongſt the thickets where the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> were lurking, hee did much hurt amongſt them, and played with his ſmall ſhot upon the reſt. <hi>The divine wiſedome can at pleaſure, and often doth infatuate the beſt counſels of men.</hi> The <hi>Bavarian</hi> Baron in all appearance to the eye of Reaſon had ſo ordered his troups, that in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, hee might conclude of a certaine victory; but what he imagined, would make for him, turned to be moſt againſt him, an higher power, to which the conqueſt muſt be aſcribed, ſo perverting his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, that what was intended for his helpe, turned to his ruine, and the ſword of God in that battell, might be apparantly ſeen above the ſword of <hi>Gede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Thoſe Regiments of foot, which were laid in Ambuſcado for the Duke of <hi>Weymar,</hi> were armed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25768:29"/>with thoſe 3 peeces of Cannon, which they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten two dayes before from him, and great ſtore of leſſer Artillery. Some troups of Cavallary were ſent from the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Army towards the Dukes, with order to fain a flight, aſſoone as the Dukes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould come neer them, that ſo they might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured to purſue them, into the trap which was laid for them: the project was hopeful, yet proved harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the <hi>Caeſareans,</hi> for the <hi>Weymariſh</hi> Colonels, <hi>Collembach</hi> &amp; <hi>Bodendorff</hi> purſued the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and made them change the nature of their flight from a counterfeit to a true one, the <hi>Infantery</hi> which lay in Ambuſcado not being able to relieve them, or helpe themſelves, ſpending their powder vainly from ſo low a ground to the hils, where the <hi>Swedes</hi> abode till they perceived the violence of the ſtorme paſt, and collected more then probably that their powder and ſhot was ſpent, and then aſſaulting thoſe poor unarmed foot men with all their power, rowted them, and regained 3 of the Cannons loſt in the former battell. The <hi>Bavarian</hi> Generall had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Garriſon of <hi>Rhinfelden,</hi> to ſally out aſſoon as the battell was joyned, and to gall the <hi>Swedes</hi> in Flank, yet this counſell was defeated to by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the Duke, who placed two troups of horſe, and one company of foot behind the hedges, by which they were to march, who looked to their charge carefully, be haved themſelves manfully, and forced the garriſon back into the City. <hi>Tupadell</hi> all this while was charging upon the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Horſe, who ſtood the firſt and ſecond ſhock bravely, but fled at the third, as unwilling to encounter with the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25768:29"/>
               <hi>Swede</hi> again. The <hi>Bavarian</hi> Generall, whoſe great heart knew not how to yield, ſtil hoped that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the day might alter, and with 1500 horſe maintained the fight, till 300 of them being ſlaine, the reſt fled leaving the lately victorious Generall with his Confederates to proove the viciſſitude of fortune, and become either examples of weakneſſe, by a timorous and confuſed flight, or the ſpoiles of time by an immature death or ſport of Fate, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment and vaſſallage, or patterns of inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy by changing their Copy, and ſerving under the Colours of their late Enemy.</p>
            <p>The totall of theſe two Battails I finde thus ſummed up.</p>
            <p>On Duke <hi>Bernhards</hi> ſide in the firſt battaile were ſlain, the Lievtenant Generall <hi>Rhinegrave Iohn Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> the <hi>Ritmaſter Barſletter,</hi> and 150 men common ſouldiers. The Generall Commiſſary <hi>Schavelitzky,</hi> the Colonell <hi>Dannenberg,</hi> Colonell <hi>Erdman,</hi> or <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach,</hi> and two Standards of <hi>Okeims</hi> Regiment, were taken priſoners, and carried into <hi>Rhinefelden.</hi> The Colonell <hi>Keller,</hi> Ritmaſter, <hi>Plech,</hi> and Captain <hi>Kein</hi> were wounded dangerouſly. In the ſecond battaile, Colonell <hi>Bodendorff,</hi> two Ritmaſters, <hi>Vorbinger</hi> and <hi>Klepper</hi> yielded to fare, with as many ordinary ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, as fell in the firſt battaile.</p>
            <p>On the Imperiall ſide in both battails, theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came priſoners of War. The Duke <hi>de Savelli,</hi> who eſcaped out of the fight, but was purſued by <hi>Roſa,</hi> and taken by <hi>Roſa,</hi> though he had diſguiſed himſelf
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25768:30"/>in the habit of a Friar; the <hi>Generaliſsimo</hi> of that Army <hi>Iohn de Werth.</hi> The Count of <hi>Enkenfourt</hi> and <hi>Sperrhewter</hi> two Generall Majors of note: Three Lievtenants Colonels the Baron <hi>de Zell, Scharftenzel</hi> and <hi>Rouger:</hi> 4 Colonels, <hi>Neinecker, Goldt, Hinderſon</hi> and <hi>Wollff</hi> 4 Majors, <hi>Rivarius, Anthony de Werth:</hi> The Major of the Generals Regiment, and <hi>Iohn Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Ionas:</hi> 17 Ritmaſters, 14 Captaines, amongſt which is a Count of <hi>Furſtenburg,</hi> 22 Lievtenants, 32 Cornets: 4 Enſignes, two <hi>Aides de Camp,</hi> ſeven Serjant Majors or Watch-maſters, 39 Corporals: one paire of Kettle-drums, 1800 foot, which tooke ſervice under the Duke of <hi>Weymar:</hi> and twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe, all which almoſt did the like; there were ſlaine upon the place in the firſt fight betwixt three and foure hundred, and in the laſt ſix hundred, and foure hundred upon the purſuite; thus the ſword was tincted in bloud that day, yet as if the dye had not been in grain, thirſted after more. Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Caeſarean</hi> horſe were gotten into <hi>Rhinefelden,</hi> and ſo eſcaped, but the next day, perceiving the Dukes great preparations to re-beſiege it, and not thinking themſelves ſecure there, would have ſought their ſafety elſewhere, and attempted to go to <hi>Briſack,</hi> but were ſurprized by the <hi>Swedes</hi> of the Dukes Army, and in a generall defeat, the Colonell <hi>Newhans Lamboy</hi> the Count <hi>Albert Lamboy,</hi> the Count <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Furſtenberg,</hi> the Baron <hi>de Ferents,</hi> and <hi>Newenſtein</hi> the Commiſſary Generall of that Army were forced to crave quarter which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and they redeemed their lives, by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a neceſſitated captivity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:25768:30"/>
The Duke thus victoriouſly quit of the Army which had undertaken to ſtop his progreſſe, makes preparation for a freſh ſiege; but before hee put it into execution, would firſt ſee his noble priſoners, and diſpoſe of them in their deſigned places. To ſupper he invited them, and entertained them with like fare generally, but not a like aſpect. <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> and <hi>Sperrheuter</hi> found themſelves not ſo well reputed or nobly welcome as the reſt. The falutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt his Highneſſe and the Generall <hi>Werth</hi> was in an ironicall complement, the Duke often jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him with ſome private nippes, by remembring ſome diſreſpective words which the Bavarian had oft ſpoke of his Highneſſe; and in fine placing him at table below the Duke of <hi>Savelli,</hi> to his greater griefe, who looked for place above him in this his eclipſed fortune, becauſe he had a command above him whileſt he was in his glory. <hi>Hinc ſurgit orexis, hinc ſtomacho bilis.</hi> This paſſage mooved the Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian to ſuch an indignation, that his wounds fel freſh a bleeding, and that he might diſhonor the duke his fellow priſoner, tranſlated the loſſe of the day from himſelfe to the others cowardiſe, unskilfulneſſe, or careleſneſſe.</p>
            <p>It could not be grievous to the Saxon Duke to heare them retort injurious words, yet as if hee had taken no pleaſure therein, hee adviſed them to give place to their fortunes, ſent for a Surgeon to dreſſe the Barons wounds, and ſupper being done ſent them to their lodgings, committing the cuſtody of their bodies to his intruſted Deputies. Then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke him to bed, but that gave him no reſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25768:31"/>remained yet to be done before he undertook a new expedition: he knew it was not his own arm which got the victory, and to aſcribe the honour to him to whom it was properly due, hee ordained a publique thankeſgiving to bee celebrated the next day at <hi>Sauffenburgh,</hi> and his priſoners were not yet in that ſphear of reſtraint to which he meant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them. Order was taken for this too: the General <hi>de Werth, Enkenfourd</hi> and ſome others were to bee tranſmitted to <hi>Benfieldt,</hi> the duke of <hi>Savelli</hi> to <hi>Lauf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenburg,</hi> and <hi>Sperrheuter, Goldt</hi> and <hi>Hinderſon</hi> to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henwiel,</hi> a ſtrong fort antiently appertaining to the duke of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> but of late ſeiſed on by the king of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and newly recovered by Duke <hi>Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard,</hi> where they are under a ſtrict watch, and more cloſely reſtrained, becauſe the duke <hi>de Savelli</hi> had eſcaped from <hi>Lauffenburg</hi> and evaded their hands.</p>
            <p>The manner of his eſcape is related diverſly: the excuſe of his Guardians making way to this fable; That a woman which waited on him to bring him victuals and dreſſe his chamber, by night let him downe by a rope from the windows of his lodging, and afterwards over the city wall. The moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is this, The perſon to whoſe truſt hee was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted had formerly ſerved under the Imperial co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and now to make his peace with the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> offered his helping hand to the Dukes eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, upon promiſe that he ſhould mediate with his maſter, procure his pardon, and reſtore him againe to grace; which the Duke accepted, vowed, &amp; was diſmiſſed ſecretly.</p>
            <p>This report is the more probable, not onely in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25768:31"/>reſpect of that aphoriſme of the Politicians, <hi>There is no truſt to be given to a reconciled enemy;</hi> but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the juridicall proceedings which enſued it: a criminall proceſſe beeing ſued out againſt a Major and two Sentinels of <hi>Schombecks</hi> regiment, and three or foure of the Burgeſſes, who were all convicted of conſpiring or conniving at the Dukes eſcape, and executed according to martiall law.</p>
            <p>The Duke eſcaped out of priſon, by conſent of his Keepers, and <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> was in hope to have been reſcued before he was brought to priſon, by ſome of his friends in deſpight of his Convoy. <hi>March</hi> 2, 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io. de Wert</hi> ſent to <hi>Briſack.</hi>
               </note> the Colonell <hi>Cullembach</hi> attended with three hundred horſe, was commanded by his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to carry the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Generall, and ſome of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers which were ſurprized with him in the laſt bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail to <hi>Benfieldt.</hi> The Garriſon of <hi>Briſack,</hi> of which the Baron was much honoured for the ſervices hee had done formerly,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Briſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kers.</hi> attempt to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue him upon the way.</note> had notice of each particular concerning that deſigne; the day, way, and number of his Guardians; (only they knew not how well they were armed, but ſuppoſed them light horſmen which were <hi>Equites cataphracti,</hi> armed <hi>Cap-a pee</hi>) &amp; made out a ſtrong party to encounter with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy, and with hazard of their lives, to attempt the recovery of the Generall. The provident Colonell, who expected ſuch adventurers, no ſooner diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, but guarded the Waggons wherin the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives were with 20 <hi>Carabins,</hi> charging his priſoners not to ſtirre upon forfeit of their lives, and his Souldiers which attended them, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons to kill the firſt which ſhould
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25768:32"/>offer to moove in hope of liberty; himſelfe and the reſt of his Retinue falling inſtantly with all their ſtrength upon the <hi>Briſſackers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defeated by <hi>Cullembach.</hi>
               </note> whom, unable to endure that ſhock, he rowted totally, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome, taking others to mercy, and ſuffering a very ſmall number to eſcape death or captivity. The way thus cleered, hee drove on without any obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle delivered up his charge at <hi>Benfeldt,</hi> and giving this inſtruction to the late Generall, to endure pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently what was beyond his power to amend; viſited <hi>Enſiſheim, Colmar</hi> and <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> which laſt City he furniſhed with many commodities, returning in liew therof, with ſtore of powder, bullets, and four great Cannon, to the Campe at <hi>Rhinefelden,</hi> which he brought thither, <hi>March</hi> 9, 19. in 22 Waggons, to haſten the period of that ſiege.</p>
            <p>Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> was now ſetled in his ſphere of activity, but the Generall <hi>de Werth</hi> cooped up, and barred from action. Til this their brains were equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly working for honorable atchievements, but now their thoughts are faſtened upon divers objects,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io. de Werth</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for <hi>Horn.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Bavarian</hi> is hammering out the way for his liberty, either by ranſome or exchange, and ſent a Trumpet towards <hi>Munchen, March</hi> 5, 15. with petitionary let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Duke his Maſter, that he might be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or exchanged for <hi>Guſtavus Horne;</hi> in which thoughts we muſt leave him; and the <hi>Saxon</hi> Duke to proſecute his victory is again returning to <hi>Rhinefel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> whither this Narration muſt follow him.</p>
            <p>Aſſoone as hee had re-begirt the Towne with his Army, it was bruited in the Campe that the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Goetz,</hi> by a ſpeedy march was comming to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25768:32"/>it; a report it was which carried ſome ſhew of truth there, being then a ceſſation of Armes, till the firſt of <hi>May</hi> new ſtile, concluded of betwixt that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall</hi> Commander, and the <hi>Heſsian</hi> Lievtenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Melander.</hi> And this ſomething delayed the Fate of the Towne; the Duke in perſon with 1500 horſe and as many foot (the reſt of his Army being then diſpoſed about <hi>Strasburgh</hi> and <hi>Briſack</hi>) going to viſit him. But the journy was ſoon accompliſhed, the grand Mountain brought forth a Mouſe, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy was only a crew of ragged <hi>Crabats</hi> and undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplined Boores, which had entrenched themſelves in the the <hi>Waldt-ſchwartz,</hi> which before the Duke could reach them were rowted and defeated by the Ritmaſter <hi>Benheuraiah,</hi> which ſhortned his Highneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Expedition, and cauſed him to returne the next day to <hi>Rhinefelden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Leaguer was laid on both ſides the River, where batteries were raiſed, and nothing omitted, which might be any way available to endamage the defendants. The Commander and Garriſon within for five days expreſſed a brave reſolution, once fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying out, and with loſſe of 80 of their owne men, making ſome ſpoile amongſt ſouldiers, from whom they carried away a Lievtenant and a Serjant as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of War. But in the end their victuals,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhinefelden</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſieged and ſurrendred.</note> and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition failing, their hearts fainted, and <hi>March</hi> 12, 22. after they perceived that <hi>Cullembach</hi> was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that his Highneſſe had ſent to <hi>Hohenwielt,</hi> for more and greater Ordnance, and made great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for the aſſault, they ſent out a Trumpet to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25768:33"/>deſire a parlee, wherein firſt were offered them the conditions of <hi>Nordlingen,</hi> and afterwards theſe enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which they accepted.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Articles granted by</hi> Bernhard <hi>Duke of</hi> Saxon, Gulick, Cleave <hi>and</hi> Bergue; Lantgrave <hi>of</hi> Thuringen, <hi>Marqueſſe of</hi> Miſnia, <hi>Count of</hi> Mark <hi>and</hi> Ravensberg, <hi>Lord of</hi> Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein, <hi>&amp;c. to the</hi> Major, <hi>and Commander in the Town of</hi> Rhinefelden.</head>
                        <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">The Articles.</note> THe Governour and Garriſon of <hi>Rhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felden</hi> ſhall be permitted to depart with their baggage, Horſes, Waggons, Wives, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; high and low armes, matches burning and Drum beating, with all the Officers and Souldiers, which are retired thither ſince the two laſt battails, except ſuch as have voluntarily come in to their party, not being preſſed therunto, who ſhall have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to depart too, but without their high Arms.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 It ſhall be lawfull for all Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Noblemen, Boors &amp; as many Burgeſſes as ſhal deſire it, to depart with the Garriſon, or afterwards with their goods and baggage, and as many as will ſtay to inhabit there, ſhal be protected from injuries, and enjoy their eſtates.</p>
                        <p n="3">3 All his Highneſſes Officers and Souldiers, which have been taken priſoners, and ſhall be found
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25768:33"/>in the Towne, ſhall be ſet at liberty without Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
                        <p n="4">4 Thoſe, which have left the Campe, without leave or Paſport, and are found to be in the Town, ſhall neither openly, nor privatly be conveyed away but left there or reſtored.</p>
                        <p n="5">5 All victuals and amunition of Warre ſhall be left in the Town, except that which the Souldiers can carry in their Knapſacks and Bandeleers.</p>
                        <p n="6">6 The wounded and ſick men which are unable to march away with the Garriſon, ſhall be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to abide in the Towne, till they can convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be carried away, or are able to follow their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
                        <p n="7">7 Aſſoon as this accord is ſealed on both ſides, the Commander ſhall be bound to open, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one of the Ports, but none of the Campe ſhall enter into the Towne thereby, till the Garriſon be departed.</p>
                        <p n="8">8 The Garriſon ſhall depart punctually on the morrow, <hi>March</hi> 14, 24 at eight in the morning.</p>
                        <p n="9">9 The Commander and Garriſon ſhall have a ſafe Convoy, and be carried neere <hi>Briſack,</hi> and for aſſurance of the Convoyes ſafety, the Commander ſhall leave behinde him ſufficient Hoſtages, which ſhall be diſmiſſed peaceably at its returne. And for the better ſurety and confirmation of this Accord, two indented Copies ſhal be drawn &amp; interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſigned and ſealed, one by the Lord and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Arſidius Forbuſh,</hi> of the one part, in the name, &amp; by the command of his Highneſſe; and the other by the preſent Governour of the Towne on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25768:34"/>part, to each of which perſons, there ſhall be one Copy delivered.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given at the Campe before, and in the Towne of of <hi>Rhinefelden,</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 13, 23. 1638.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This agreement was more truly obſerved amongſt Enemies in this time of War, then many civill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts are amongſt neighbours in time of peace, 600 <hi>Imperiall</hi> Souldiers left the Town the next morning, to the <hi>Victor,</hi> but were not all conveiged to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke,</hi> yet none were detained violently, the Convoy was ready for as many would make uſe of it, but two hundred of them preſently offered their ſervice, to the Duke of <hi>Weymar,</hi> and the moſt part of the reſt, no ſooner underſtood of the place to which they were deſigned, but they did the like, more fearing the famine, which already rages there, then hoping for reliefe from theſe inhabitants and preſidiaries. The time ſpent before the Towne was not loſt, it being a place of ſtrength and importance, and honoring the Dukes atchievement, with eleven Enſignes which were ſaved there in the laſt battell and two old Enſignes belonging to <hi>Pappenheims</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, which eſcaped and were kept there, ſince the battell of <hi>Lutzen:</hi> beſides the gain of two faire Culverings, many Bullets, yet but one Quintall of powder, and ſome ſmall ſtore of proviſions.</p>
            <p>His work is not yet done. The care of the Town was committed to <hi>Forbuſh,</hi> who imployed himſelf to repaire the breaches, ſupply the Magazine, and to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25768:34"/>work about new Fortifications, while the Duke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth of his Army (now grown ſtronger by 6000 men than it was in the firſt battell,
<note place="margin">The Dukes proceedings.</note> and dayly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a freſh ſupply of a thouſand, who by that time were come as far as <hi>Monbeliard</hi>) one part part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was ſent againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Rotelu,</hi> where they forced the garriſon to yeeld upon diſcretion, retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſouldiers in their pay, but detaining their pay, but detaining their Captain and his Lievtenant priſoners: and found an hundred Muyds of wine, much corne, cattell, and other proviſion, which ſhould have bin tranſported to <hi>Briſack:</hi> another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Roſa</hi> toward <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> who had before taken in <hi>Duthlinguen,</hi> a paſſage upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> and ſome other places, himſelfe going with the groſſe of his army towards <hi>Fryburg,</hi> a towne in <hi>Briſgaw</hi> three leagues from <hi>Briſack,</hi> which as they write from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill</hi> is already ſenſible of the inconveniences which attend them by his neighbourhood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a part of the third Chapter the titles over the head beeing</hi> Occurrences in the Netherlands, <hi>ſhould be</hi> Occurrences in upper Germany.</p>
            <div type="history">
               <head>
                  <hi>Further Occurrences in the</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands.</head>
               <p>The jollity in the Netherlands before ſpoken of, bore a reſemblance of a firme peace, and their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs might have made a ſtranger beleeve, that the States of the united Provinces were then ſo ſecure,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25768:35"/>as they needed neither feare any hoſtility of an open enemy, nor the clandeſtine practiſes of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. But <hi>Novit paucos ſecura quies,</hi> the condition of all ſublunary things is ſubject to change, and <hi>The ſmiles of Fortune are more to bee ſuſpected than her frownes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cardinal Infant a potent adverſary, and one which tugged not meerely for honour, but laboured as much to reduce that Ariſtocracie to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Crowne of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which claimed a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and dominion over the ſeventeene Provinces by marriage with the daughter and heire to the houſe of <hi>Burgundy;</hi> as they to preſerve it, made ſtrong preparation againſt them both by ſea and land; and ſome ſecret conſpirators (the more dangerous by their privacy; for God defend me from my friends, ſaith the Italian, and from my foes I will guard my ſelfe) inhabitants and garriſon ſoldiers of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> had plotted treacherouſly to deliver up that city in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Spaniards: who attending the time for execution, had drawn together ſix or ſeven thouſand men, and lay neer the city, wel provided of ſcaling ladders &amp; other military inſtruments. The chief conſpirators were <hi>Veynck</hi> a friar,
<note place="margin">A treaſon at Maſtricht.</note> Padre Rector of the Minorites, <hi>Iohn Lundſman</hi> or <hi>moone</hi> a Brewer, <hi>Claudi de la Cour</hi> a Burgundian gentleman and his wife, two Burgundian ſouldiers of <hi>Hauterives</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and two Brick-layers inhabitants of the city; and their plot was layd thus, and thus diſcovered: The Brewers houſe was ſited upon the ſmall River of <hi>Ecker</hi> behinde the Cloyſter of the Minorites, and abutted neere the port <hi>de noſtre Dame,</hi> at a place
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25768:35"/>where formerly there had been a Poſterne, but was made up ſlightly in the time of the laſt ſiege. This weakneſſe in the wall he firſt diſcovered to the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundian and <hi>La Cour,</hi> who willing to returne to the Spaniard from whom they had revolted, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping there by to get both gold and honour, firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it by private letters to the governor of <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> and being incouraged by him, revealed it to the Brick-layers, promiſing them a good ſum of money to breake downe the new building privatly. <hi>La Cour</hi> whoſe pregnant braine longed to bee delivered of this monſtrous conception, while it was an Embrio, appointed a certaine day March the firſt new ſtile, for its birth, and to facilitate the worke for his mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives the Brick-layers, often repaired to the place, ſurveyed it diligently, and obſerved the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt the thicknes of the old wall &amp; ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the new; til at laſt being ſeene by a Burger, ſuſpected as a Spy becauſe hee was an Alien, and threatned with the Racke <hi>(neſcit tacere commiſſorum ſcelerum trepidatio)</hi> confeſſed the treaſon &amp; his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices therein.
<note place="margin">Diſcovered.</note> His confeſſion ſaved him from that torture, but not his fellow Conſpirators, who being detected by him, and ſeized on by the officers, at firſt denied the fact, and ſtood upon their juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But it is vaine to plead not guilty, before ſuch as conclude them ſo: The Padre Rector pleaded his monaſtick life, which being piouſly contemplative, could not entertaine any ſuch vile intentions: the Brewer and Burgundian gentlewoman pretended their infranchiſement in that city (the one beeing a free Denizen by birth, the other by purchaſe)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25768:36"/>which muſt or ſhould engage them to loyalty, and arme them againſt treachery. The brick-layer (for one fled) pleaded ignorance, confeſſing the matter <hi>de facto,</hi> but excuſing his intention by circumſtance, ſaying that he worked for wages, that he was hired therunto by the Padre Rector and the brewer, who claimed an inlet and outlet by that poſterne, in and from the city, and that this was the onely end for which they conſented to undertake it. But the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and commander, knew that of old <hi>Catiline</hi> who was a native Roman, as well as of late their <hi>Barnevelt,</hi> that a cloyſter hath ſometimes bin a cage for unclean birds, and that hell-hatched treaſon doth not ſeldom palliate it ſelfe with the borrowed garb of ſeeming ſanctity; That no man could or ought to be ſo ignorat, as not to know, there are any private proprietaries in the walls of a city, which are <hi>Bonum publicum,</hi> and not to be broken down for any privat mans uſe, without licenſe, tooke not their words for a ſatisfactory anſwer, but try if the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall racke would inforce that from them, which their ſeduced conſciences, though laſhed with a dumbe beadle, could not make them to reveale. The firſt torture wreſted out the truth from all, but the Frier, who bore his firſt torture with a Stoicke apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, and though accuſed by the reſt joyntly, as the firſt moover of this divelliſh engine, denied all, till the ſecond tortures being preſented him, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with feare, he opened himſelfe really, begging that mercy humbly, which had hee not beene falſe he might have enjoyed freely, but could not now expect. He was ſentenced to be firſt degraded, then
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:25768:36"/>executed: but the Ordinary proceeding ſlowly, as not willing to have ſuch ſhame fall upon the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the execution was not done till the end of May.
<note place="margin">And the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors executed.</note> The others ſuffered Aprill 20, 30, had their heads cut off, and ſet upon high poles (long living witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their perfidiouſneſſe) behinde the Minorites Cloyſter, with their faces toward the Sconce. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagi de la Cour</hi> was quartered, and the foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſet upon the foure gates, thoſe towards <hi>Bruxels</hi> and the <hi>Boſh,</hi> Saint <hi>Peters</hi> and the <hi>Wyck</hi> port, but the bodies of the others were buried.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One day giveth a remedy to the troubles of another.</hi> The magiſtrat and commander in <hi>Maſtricht</hi> had bin much perplexed with this intended treaſon, becauſe after the execution of the firſt revealed conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, they found others both Churchmen and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of note, to have conſented thereunto; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore apprehending them and committing them to priſon, they intended to take vengeance of their profeſſed enemies, who had prompted their people to this prodition. In the Cloyſter or Abby of <hi>Beff,</hi> which ſtands beſides <hi>Hanuyt</hi> and <hi>Namur,</hi> lay five companies of Spaniſh horſe, and two of foot, and thitherward the Viſcount of <hi>de Turenne,</hi> General of the army newly formed in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Liege,</hi> for the ſervice of the Chriſtian King,
<note place="margin">The Abbey of Beſt plundered by the Vicount <hi>Turenne.</hi>
                  </note> marched with his own Cavallery and the horſe of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> foure hundred foot and two pieces of ordnance, Aprill 2, 12. The next day following they appeared before the Cloyſter early in the morning; when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh horſemen diſcovering them, preſently moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and fled for their owne ſafety, leaving their own
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25768:37"/>baggage, the foot, and the religious people to bee a prey for the aſſailants, who tooke the Abbot, a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, a Sergeant, and a hundred common men pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, pillaged the Abby, burnt down a fair houſe which ſtood neere it; and the next day met with a party of Imperiall horſe, whom they defeated, and tooke from them ſixty horſes, which with the ſpoil of the Abbey, and the priſoners taken there, they returned into <hi>Maſtricht.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Spaniard loſt there by land, hee got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with advantage about the ſame time by ſea: five ſhips of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the white Swan, the black Lion, and three other comming from the Streights laden with rich merchandiſe, fell into their hands and became their lawfull prize. A frigat of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerke</hi> chaſed the white Swan when it was almoſt at home and tooke it. Two other Frigats purſued, burnt and ſunke the blacke Lion, which alone was valued worth five or ſix tunne of gold, yet got no other ſpoile but ſixteene men, which alone eſcaped the fury of the ſea by the mercy of their enemies who tooke them priſoners and brought them into <hi>Dunkerk.</hi> The other three fell into the mouth of the Spaniſh navy neere the Bay of <hi>Biſcay,</hi> and were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to yeeld. This loſſe came into the foot of the Hollanders account, who by their owne computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the loſſe of the <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> which comming from <hi>Fernambuck</hi> laden with foure hundred &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cheſts of ſugar, and other rich wares, was caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon the coaſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had then loſt within the ſpace of a few moneths ſix and twenty ſayle of ſhips.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:25768:37"/>
Now the Spring was well entred, the Sunne had cloathed the earth in a greene ſuit, and exhaling the moyſture, which made the high-wayes pulpiſh and unfit for man or beaſt to tread upon, began againe to make them paſſable; when both the Cardinall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant and the States prepared againſt each other for an offenſive and defenſive war. <hi>Iſthoe eſt ſapere non quod ante pedes modo eſt videre, ſed etiam illa quae futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſunt:</hi> Wiſedome conſidereth how it ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, as well as what it ſhould doe: A wiſe man loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as well behinde him as before him, both in peace and war.</p>
               <p>Before either part went to field, their firſt care was to ſecure thoſe places which were moſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to danger. To this end the Count <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw</hi> was ſent by the Prince Cardinall, to view and fortifie with victuals and amunition, the forts and cities upon the <hi>Maze,</hi> as <hi>Genue, Geldri, Venlo</hi> &amp; <hi>Rure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund:</hi> as the cavallery of the States was diſpatched from the <hi>Boſch, Hueſdon, Emmerick, Rees, Nimmegen. Weſel,</hi> and other places towards the <hi>Grave</hi> and the <hi>Maze,</hi> for the ſame purpoſe. The French on the South ſide, which menaced the Cardinal as ill as the Hollanders on the North, required contribution of the Brabantiers, threatning ſuch as ſhould deny it: and the Cardinall Infant publiſhed an Edict at <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> Aprill 13, 23. in the name of the Catholique King, wherein hee ſtraitly charged all his ſubjects not to pay it: adding withall, that hee which could bring in any of the French Agents which came to demand it, ſhould receive for his guerdon fifty Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: and commanding all victuallers and inholders
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25768:38"/>in cities or villages, not to lodge or entertaine any ſuch French gueſts, though their neere kinſmen or deareſt friends, upon the paine of five and twenty gilders: enjoyning alſo ſtrict watch to be kept upon all towers and ſteeples, and the Boores to arm upon the firſt alarme: and becauſe hee was ſurrounded with enemies, by advice of his Councel of War it was concluded, that <hi>Don Andrea Cautelmo</hi> ſhould be Generall of the foot, and the Marqueſſe <hi>Sfondrato,</hi> of the horſe in <hi>Brabant,</hi> Count <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> in the North of <hi>Flanders;</hi> and Prince <hi>Thomaſo, Balanſo,</hi> and <hi>Iſolani,</hi> in the Southweſt <hi>Henault</hi> and <hi>Artois,</hi> who then began to appear about Saint <hi>Aumars</hi> &amp; <hi>Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> Yet that this order ſhould bee changed upon occaſion, and doubled all his garriſons upon the frontiers of <hi>Picardy.</hi> Whileſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was muſtring up his forces, which by the 12, 22, of May, he had conveyed by ſhallops to their Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous at <hi>Lithoyen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince Cardinall was rather upon a defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive than offenſive war, and ſtood looking a while where the ſtorme would fall. The Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> removed from his firſt rendezvous to <hi>Berghen up Zoom,</hi> where he lay with the maine of his Army ſome dayes together, but about the end of May and beginning of Iune: Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> was ſent with ſixe thouſand men to invade <hi>Flanders,</hi> and like a ſweeping raine which drives all before it; ſcarce finding oppoſition, tooke in the ſconces of <hi>Verbroeck,
<note place="margin">Count <hi>Will. Naſſaw</hi> at the Blocker-dyke.</note> Steland,</hi> and <hi>Callo,</hi> and at laſt aſſaulted the <hi>Mary-ſconce,</hi> the principall of all upon the <hi>Blocker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike,</hi> was maſter of an half-moon, which he held for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:25768:38"/>the ſpace of twelve houres, yet then was beaten from it by the garriſon.</p>
               <p>The Cardinall Inſant beeing advertiſed hereof, and knowing how <hi>Antwerpe</hi> the nobleſt Empery of the Weſt and Marquiſate of the Empire was indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, if thoſe neighbouring ſconces ſhould remain in the fingers of the Hollanders and united States, drew all his forces together to ſtop his further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. Some troupes he ſent before him, to skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh with the aſſailants and hinder them from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, while himſelfe with the groſſe of his Army might bee ready. The avauntgard of the Spaniſh marched ſo faſt, that Iune 7, 17, they had fought with a party of Hollanders whom they found with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their quarters, where the commander of that Holland party <hi>Maurice</hi> the only ſon of Count <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am de Naſſaw,</hi> an hopefull young gentleman wiſe and valiant, fell by two mortall wounds, the one by a musket bullet ſhot into his breaſt, and the other by a Rapier run through his belly.</p>
               <p>The Count <hi>Piccolomini,</hi> by this time was come to <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> to aide the Prince Cardinall, who calling <hi>Groebendoncy</hi> to counſell with them, <hi>Iune</hi> 10, 20, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to aſſault the Count <hi>William</hi> in his Quarters with all their forces, and the ſame night proſecuted the courſe on which they had concluded. The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Army conſiſting of eight full Regiments, was divided into three ſeverall parts under theſe three Generals, and led along the Dike towards <hi>Callo, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veren</hi> and <hi>Verbroeck,</hi> that they might fall upon the <hi>States</hi> Army at once in its three ſeverall Quarters, the firſt of Count <hi>William,</hi> the ſecond Colonell <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reutters,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:25768:39"/>and the third the <hi>Scots</hi> Quarter. The aſſaults began at twelve in the night, and continued untill 8 the next morning with ſuch fury, that the reports of the Guns were heard five leagues off, the defendants neither being terrified by the number of the aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants,
<note place="margin">Is aſſaulted by the Cardinall Infant.</note> nor the aſſaylants diſheartned by the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants courage, and well ordered fight. It was too violent a ſtorme to laſt longer, for the ground began already to be dyed with the bloud of the ſlain men, and how long ſhould the ſword devoure? The ſlaughtered corſps muſt have a ſepulture, and both parties gave free licence for buriall of the dead. Till then, neither of their loſſes appeared but now, the <hi>States</hi> found ſome Officers of note ſlaine, as Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonell <hi>Hinderſon,</hi> the Lieutenant Colonel to the Lord of <hi>Beverwerth,</hi> Serjeant Major <hi>Levenſtein,</hi> and foure others, Captains and Lieutenants, beſides above 400 common men. The Cardinall <hi>Infants</hi> loſſe exceeded this, there being above 3000 of his ſouldiers found dead upon the ground, beſides ſuch as were wounded; and himſelfe being as ſenſible of the loſſe of his men, as of his own honour, preſently renewed the aſſault, and continued it without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<note place="margin">And, forced to Bie.</note> ſo furiouſly, that the Count of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> was forced to flie in a ſtorme, and returne the ſame way which he came, leaving behinde him eight cannons, two great ſhallops, and 60 leſſer, 2300 of his men priſoners, and almoſt as many ſlaine by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and ſtifled in the myre.</p>
               <p>How unexpectedly may the deſignes of men be fruſtrated? The Provinces under the Catholike King, ſeemed till this day to be almoſt under the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25768:39"/>command of the Chriſtian King, and United States; But the fortune of this day (to which Heaven it ſelfe aſſented, by contrary windes,
<note place="margin">The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of this victory.</note> hindering three Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſent by water, upon the information of the Lievtenant to the Count of <hi>Solms, Iune,</hi> 11, 21 in the morning, of the former nights work, to the aſſiſtance of Count <hi>William,</hi> from comming unto him) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the ſtate of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government; the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who then lay with his Army at <hi>Nord gheeſt,</hi> inſtead of invading, was fain to lie upon a defenſive ward; the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> with his own forces was able to deal alone with his diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men; the Forts lately gotten by the States were yielded up. <hi>Enreutter</hi> retyring as well as hee could from the <hi>Verborech</hi> Sconce, the <hi>Scots</hi> forced to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render the other, and <hi>Piccolomini</hi> with 11000 men had opportunity, to aide the Prince <hi>Thomaſo,</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> in the Southweſt of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chaſtillon</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Marſhall, having paſſed the Sommer, <hi>May</hi> 8, 18 brought his Army to the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Paul, May</hi> 12, 22.
<note place="margin">The Caſtles of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </note> which he preſently ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned and had ſurrendred unto him upon theſe conditions; that the Governour and the Garriſon both horſe and foot ſhould march out with baggage and arms half an houre after the Capitulation, and ſafely goe to <hi>Bethune;</hi> that the inhabitants of the place might have leave to do the ſame with like aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance: that they ſhould be conducted by a hundred horſe of <hi>Caſsions</hi> Regiment a league upon the way; and thence by the Trumpet of the ſame company, with a Paſport to <hi>Bethune,</hi> and that the inhabitants religious perſons or others, might have liberty to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25768:40"/>remain there (if they pleaſed) taking the Oath of Alleagiance to the Chriſtian King, which conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being ſigned and ſubſcribed, there marched out 120 men, above 300 women and children in Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and the Fort was Garriſoned with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Navarre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Halfe a league from thence ſtood the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Martin de Freſne</hi> a paſſage of importance,
<note place="margin">Saint <hi>Martin de Freſne.</hi>
                  </note> and a ready way for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> to Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> This he ſummoned the ſame night, and having prepared to aſſault it, the Garriſon capitulated upon the ſame termes, as the former, and the <hi>French</hi> Marſhall laid into it 50 Muſqueties under the command of a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant the day following. <hi>May</hi> 13, 23. the Marſhall encamped neere <hi>Perne</hi> where there was a Fort,
<note place="margin">Perne.</note> but abandoned by the people, whoſe haſty flight cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to leave behinde them great ſtore of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage, corn, and cattle. The Country about it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned with forrage, and thither the Marſhall ſent ſome of his forces to make proviſion for the Horſe, who returned at night with a good booty, &amp; 600 priſoners, able to pay their ranſomes; beſides the Religious perſons and women, whom diſmiſſed freely, yet hanged up ſome <hi>Boutefeue</hi> for example ſake, and ſo abated their number.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 14, 24, the <hi>French</hi> Army came to <hi>Theronenna</hi> a place famouſed by Hiſtorians, where the remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ruines of the buildings, are ſtill witneſſes of its ancient glory. The inhabitants loath to alter their government retired preſently into the Church, which ſtandeth in an Iland of the River, and thence made ſome unhappy ſhot againſt the <hi>French;</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25768:40"/>three volleys of Cannon bullets, they yielded, and ſome being ſlain, the reſt were taken priſoners.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Therovenne,</hi> and other Forts and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyes taken by the French.</note> And now the Army, <hi>May</hi> 15, 25. tooke up its Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters betwixt <hi>Ardres</hi> &amp; <hi>Blandeck,</hi> a quarter of a league from Saint <hi>Aamers,</hi> upon the River <hi>Aa,</hi> which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth down to <hi>Graveling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before hee raiſed any bank againſt the City, or would give order for the Circumvallation thereof, the Marſhall diſpatched 3000 foot, and 2000 horſe with two Culverings, two peeces of 12 pound Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and other neceſſary equipage under <hi>Fert Imbaut,</hi> to cheer the Spaniſh Forts,
<note place="margin">The ſiege of Saint <hi>Omars.</hi>
                  </note> betwixt <hi>Ardres</hi> and Saint <hi>Omar,</hi> that he might have a free paſſage for his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualers and Convoyes; and himſelfe with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Officers went to ſcoure the cauſey-wayes, which were filled with armed Peaſants, and might otherwiſe have much impeached him in his deſigne. Both theſe parties did their Offices in the ſpace of two days, the Colonel <hi>Ferte Imbaut,</hi> having firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in three ſmall Forts which ſtood upon the way, then the Caſtle, <hi>de Maule,</hi> which was defended by a good Garriſon, and ſome peeces of Cannon, and laſtly the Fort <hi>d' Eſper legue,</hi> which after the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of 36 <hi>Walloons,</hi> 10 <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and 150 <hi>Payſants,</hi> was committed to the care of the Governour of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> who put into it an Officer with 80 ſouldiers, which promiſed to keepe it eight dayes, or till 1000 Cannon ſhot were made againſt it, though it ſhould be ſurrounded with the Enemies Army. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall himſelfe defeated, the 700 Peaſants which guarded the cauſey-wayes, took in the Fort <hi>de Mew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foſſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:25768:41"/>or <hi>Newdike,</hi> and the Abbey of <hi>Clermarais;</hi> and to leave no rub in the way, <hi>Hallier</hi> took the Abbey of <hi>Watiene,</hi> where the Count <hi>de Fountaine</hi> lay, and had much ado to ſave himſelfe, whilſt for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at the laſt houre, and at the ſame time, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>de la Ferte</hi> took by aſſault <hi>Saubrevit,</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillon Sommeline,</hi> by the ſurprize wherof Saint <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars</hi> was fully blocked up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A faire houſe well ſited,
<note place="margin">The deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Saint <hi>Omars.</hi>
                     </note> and fitted with competent demeſnes, never wants clamours in the propriety: nor a rich wel qualified Virginſuiters:</hi> ſuch was the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Saint <hi>Omars,</hi> a place of as much pleaſure as conſequence, yet giving pregnant teſtimonies of both, to compaſſe which, the <hi>French</hi> left no ſtone unmoved, nor the Cardinall Infant to preſerve it.</p>
               <p>This City a part of the Territories, of the ancient Morines ſubdued by <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> was begun by a Biſhop of <hi>Therovenna,</hi> who built there a Monaſtery called by his owne name, and by his ſuppoſed ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie <hi>(devotion in that time of ſuperſtition, commonly cauſing a confluence of people)</hi> made it very populous. It is at this preſent reckoned in the ſecond Ranke of the Cities of <hi>Flanders,</hi> well flankered and fortified, being in the territories of <hi>France,</hi> of ſtately building throughout the Abbey, eſpecially which is the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt endowed of al the Covents in that country. The <hi>French</hi> Marſhall that he might have more freedome to ſettle his Army before it, <hi>May</hi> 18, 28. gave order to 1000 horſe,
<note place="margin">The order of the ſiege.</note> and 1200 foot, to repaire unto his head quarter, the ſame day by noone, but his men
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25768:41"/>not meeting at the peremptory houre, hee deferred his deſigne till the day following; his intention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be maſter of a Ferry, by which paſſengers were tranſported into the City. It was an attempt of a great ſpirit, with ſo ſmall a number, without defenſive coverture, to encounter with almoſt as many, who had immured themſelves with earthen walls, and were by that meanes almoſt ſhot-free. Two Regiments of <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Walloons,</hi> were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Prince <hi>Thomaſo</hi> to guard the place, which perceiving the <hi>French</hi> almoſt upon them, ſpent their powder prodigally, againſt the aſſaylants which in fine, forced them to leave their Trenches, and caſt themſelves diſorderly into a Ferry-boat, and ſeven or eight other Bottomes which they had prepared for their uſe, and ſo prevented them of their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which was to entrench themſelves there, that they might keep the way open for importation of men, and victuals into the City. This Rub thus taken away, and the <hi>French</hi> Army re-enforced with 27 new Companies, the lines of circumvallation were drawne out, <hi>Iune</hi> 2, new ſtile, which though they were of ſo large an extent as five leagues in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, the pioners with the help of the common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers promiſed to finiſh, or at the leaſt make defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in the ſpace of eight dayes, if they were not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army.</p>
               <p>Five or ſix days paſſed without any action com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced by the <hi>Spaniard</hi> againſt the Aſſaylants:
<note place="margin">A French cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of horſe; ſurprized by <hi>Forgatz.</hi>
                  </note> and then <hi>Forgatzs</hi> the <hi>Crabat,</hi> with his Regiment was advanced to aire a place, two leagues and a half di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:25768:42"/>from Saint <hi>Omars;</hi> where having nottice, that a <hi>French</hi> Captain of Horſe by name <hi>Vitenvvall,</hi> was ſcouring the field, accompanied with twenty men at Arms, he ſent out 200 horſe againſt them, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the <hi>French Cavallary,</hi> and having firſt deadly wounded him, took the Captain priſoner. This at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement prompted the <hi>Crabats</hi> to an higher at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which was to aſſault the Quarter of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Ferte Imbaut,</hi> which they did, with 200 men, boldly though not happily, theſe being beaten back to the groſſe of the Regiment, which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, if not endangered upon this occaſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chambot</hi> a Captain of Horſe, and <hi>Valliere</hi> a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to the Field-marſhall, had been abroad with 200 men of Arms; who upon their return, were within a quarter of a league of the Marqueſſe his Quarter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Forgatz</hi> defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> at the time when it was aſſaulted by the <hi>Crabats,</hi> when hearing the Alarme, they ſpurred up to helpe their Comrades, and over-reaching the Arriere of the <hi>Crabats</hi> in their retreat, purſued them to the place, where their companions expected them, when <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatz (as feare alwayes preſents the worſt of dangers to the imagination)</hi> ſuppoſing himſelf caught in a trap, and dreaming of an Ambuſcado, fled confuſedly, leaving 30 of his ſouldiers ſlaine by the French <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallters,</hi> and himſelf purſued to the gates of <hi>Aire</hi> his Garriſon.</p>
               <p>Fortune this day played her own part, and ſhewed apparantly her mutability. The ſame time <hi>Iune</hi> 9, 19 two Regiments that <hi>d'Eſpagny</hi> and <hi>Fouqueſoles,</hi> were commanded by the French Marſhall to march to <hi>Momclin,</hi> or the <hi>Feroy-fort,</hi> to ſecure it from the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards;</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:25768:42"/>but the next way not ſerving for the portage of their Waggons and Baggage,
<note place="margin">Saint <hi>O murs</hi> ſuccoured by Prince <hi>Thoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi>
                  </note> they were forced to take a compaſſe of two leagues, and in the way, re-encountred with Prince <hi>Thomaſo,</hi> attended with 2000 horſe, and 4000 foot, who encloſed them with his troups, and with the loſſes of above twenty of them, amongſt which was the ſecond ſonne of the Camp-maſter <hi>d'Eſpagny,</hi> who was wounded, &amp; made a priſoner with his third ſonne, Lievrenant to his brother, and <hi>Fouqueſoks</hi> forcing them to yield upon compoſition, thruſt in 800 freſh men into the City, which were carried over in boats, by the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels out out through the <hi>Moraſſe,</hi> ſent from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One place is ſometime fortunate to one party, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to another.</hi> By the ſame way which the Prince <hi>Thomaſo</hi> re-enforced the Garriſon <hi>Piccolomini,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Iuly,</hi> relieved it with victuals, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition; the <hi>French</hi> Army by <hi>Iune</hi> 5, 15. had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified themſelves in their earthen walls. <hi>Chaſtillon</hi> had his Quarter at the head of the <hi>Moraſſe. Hallier</hi> had his next to the Marſhall, and ſo the reſt of the Colonels reſpectively. Three ſtrong Redoubts were built in the place betwixt the <hi>Ferry</hi> and <hi>Hallier:</hi> Two Forts upon the plain of <hi>Nieube;</hi> the Marſhal <hi>la Force,</hi> was come to the Campe with his Army; the batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were raiſed, the Ordnance played, the Towne was ſo ſtraight beſieged, that there was neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe nor egreſſe for any; Famine beganne to rage within,
<note place="margin">Saint <hi>Omars</hi> relieved by <hi>Piccolomini.</hi>
                  </note> the inhabitants and preſidiaries were in three weeks brought to a ſmall allowance of meate, and that none of the beſt, the powder and Ammunition
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:25768:43"/>began to faile, the <hi>French</hi> ſeemed as full of fire and courage, as their ſtomacks were of victuals, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the victory, ſang an <hi>Epinicion.</hi> But <hi>Iuly</hi> 4, 14. the Scene altered, <hi>Piccolomini</hi> projected a way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, and by the courage of Serjant Major <hi>Norris,</hi> who that day commanded an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regiment, and led the Avantguard in the Expedition, performed it. It is thus related by Letters from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and reported to mee by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman who was in the Action.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piccolomini</hi> directed the Generall <hi>Norris</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Walloon</hi> Regiment to attend as neer the <hi>Ferry</hi> as they could, without being diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whilſt himſelfe with his forces might either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe <hi>Hallier,</hi> or with advantage aſſault him in his Quarters. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commander took the charge upon him, and while the <hi>Italian</hi> Count with skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and pretenſes of a ſharp battail held the <hi>French</hi> in play, conveyed (at noon day) 1000 men, 300 barrels of powder, and as much Bread, Cheeſe, and Bacon, as loaded 400 Waggons by land, by Boat into the City; which being afterward made known to the <hi>French</hi> Field-marſhals, as loath to conſume themſelves there, they retyred orderly towards <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres;</hi> with the loſſe of their hopes of gaining Saint <hi>Omars,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſiiege is raiſed,</note> getting a ſmall victory upon the Prince <hi>Thomaſo</hi> Colleague to <hi>Piccolomini</hi> in this action, in his return cutting off 1500 of his men; and ſeizing of 1200 of his horſe, which they ſent the next day to <hi>Calis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:25768:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Further Occurrences in the upper</hi> Germany.</head>
               <p>April the firſt new ſtile, was the day when the Saxon Duke firſt raiſed a banke before <hi>Frey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> Some other pieces ſtood in his way, and hee ſpent a few dayes to take them in, before he pitched his Campe there, though there wanted no induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to perſwade him to haſten thither as namely the ſcituation of the place, it beeing an inlet into <hi>Switzerland</hi> from <hi>Swaben,</hi> a falſe report of a ſlender garriſon, the weakeneſſe of the fortifications, and the Imperiall preparations againſt him, <hi>Goetz</hi> being already upon his march with thoſe forces which he had under him, to meet the Generall <hi>Walh</hi> and his troupes, and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who was forming of an army about the <hi>Danuby,</hi> and was expected in perſon with the Duke <hi>de Savelli,</hi> to bring it down to <hi>Nordlingen;</hi> the generall Rendezvous of the Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans and Bavarians, which were joyntly to oppoſe him.</p>
               <p>The Caſtle of <hi>Roetele</hi> or <hi>Rotelen,</hi> the Key of the Marquiſate of <hi>Dourlack,</hi> guarded with 70 Preſidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, was the firſt place which preſented it ſelf to his eye, <hi>March</hi> 27, 7. the Duke of <hi>Weymar</hi> ſummoned it, and next Sunday being Palme-ſunday carried it, forcing both the Commander and the Souldiers to yield upon diſcretion. The Caſtle was well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Ammunition, and that with the Citadell, though he might juſtly have reſerved it to his own uſe, he gave to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Dourlach,</hi> who was then in the Campe, and by this atchievment ſeemed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25768:44"/>to gain a new poſſeſſion, and re-inveſtiture into his inheritance which he had been deprived of, ever ſince the fatall battell of <hi>Nordlinguen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The day of this conqueſt ſeemed to bring as good an Augury to the growing hopes of the Marqueſſe, as the Palme which grew at the feet of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue did to him before the battell in <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> though he was newly poſſeſt of this fort, he would not make his perſonall abode there, but committed the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to ſome ſelected ſouldiers, and himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied the Army which hitherto went on pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly. <hi>Roſa</hi> was commanded immediatly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Danuby,</hi> where he encountred and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited one Company of Imperiall Horſe, and a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Crabats,</hi> and a thouſand Horſe, and ſome Foot were ſent back toward the <hi>Rhine</hi> to make head againſt <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and young <hi>Mercie</hi> who were comming with a Convoy of 40 Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons loaden with Corn and Salt to re-victuall <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack</hi> whom they defeated, and therupon tooke in <hi>Newenburg</hi> a place of good ſtrength upon the River (but then abandoned by the Imperialiſts who were fled from thence for feare of the Dukes forces) and then having laid in a competent Garriſon returned to the Army, which by that time was newly ſet down before <hi>Freyburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſiege here was of more difficulty then was at firſt imagined:
<note place="margin">The ſiege and taking of <hi>Frey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
                  </note> The Town was well fortified with a ſtrong wall and deep ditch, well mann'd with 900 reſolved ſouldiers, and inhabitants as reſolute for the defence of the City as were the men of War. The field afforded no convenient place, where the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:25768:44"/>Duke might plant his Ordnance for battery: The Towne was abutted withthree Suburbs which hee firſt tooke in, and after imployed them to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: There he mounted his Cannon, which by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten diſcharging made an aſſaultable breach in the wall, and then he gave order for the aſſault, which was undertaken by his ſouldiers cheerfully; but not ſucceſſefully. The Ditch was deeper then it was ſuppoſed, the ſcaling Ladders were too ſhort to reach the loweſt part of the broken wall, the beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all ſorts, Religious perſons, old men, women, &amp; children repaired thither, to make it good againſt the aſſaylants, and with musket ſhot, ſtones, Grena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, and wild fire beat them off, having ſlain the Lievtenant Colonell to whom that ſervice was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, and forty common men beſides our worthy Country man and reſolute Gentleman Maſter <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cambell,</hi> whoſe ſtory is thus related to mee by Captain <hi>Iohn Scot</hi> who was a coactor, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Army at that Expedition.
<note place="margin">A worthy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of two Engliſh Gentlemen, but unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</note> A Lievtenant by name <hi>Sandelands</hi> being upon the top of the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſeeing the hearts of the ordinary men to faile, looking back, called to <hi>Cambell,</hi> ſecond me, let us not loſe the Honour which our Nation hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with bloud, which he did; theſe Colleagues in that ſervice, aſſiſted only with two Dutch Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and a Scottiſh Serjant of the Red Regiment, behaving themſelves ſo bravely, that in deſpight of the defendants, they ſcaled the breach, ſlew ſome of thoſe, which mayntained it, and put the Burgers into ſuch a Feare, that as they confeſſed afterwards,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:25768:45"/>they had then begged quarter, had they not at the inſtant perceived the ſmal number of the aſſaylants. <hi>But an Apoplexie is cured by a Fever,</hi> Anger doth chaſe away Feare, and now offended with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for ſtarting at a ſhadow, the Souldiers and Townſmen came on furiouſly, wounded both <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delands</hi> and <hi>Cambell,</hi> who for all this went on and ſent one ſoul more to <hi>Charons</hi> Ferry, when a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Gentleman marking how bravely <hi>Cambell</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved, ſhot, and wounded him mortally, throwing him not yet dead barbarouſly into the midſt of a burning pile, which was ready for their defence, <hi>Sandelands</hi> in the mean time retyring, and though charged by the Enemy returning ſafely, by the valour of a Souldier, who with his Piſtoll kept the ſealing ladder, for his ſafe Retreat.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Bernherd</hi> was not a little moved with this loſſe, yet <hi>as the pureſt ſpirits are moſt active,</hi> in the heat, reneweth and increaſeth his batteries, lengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his ladders, and prepares for a freſh aſſault. The preparations of a potent Adverſary are terrible to a weak one, he was obſerved by the Garriſon, and without more blows the Town capitulated, and was ſurrendred <hi>Ap.</hi> 5, new ſtile. Thus this City once the Metropolis and Capitall of the <hi>Briſgow,</hi> at this preſent more glorious, though not ſo ſtrong as <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack,</hi> changed her Lord; a City famous for the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy, famous for excellent Rock, Chryſtall, ſome of it being of that bigneſſe, that a cup therof, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning two Engliſh quarts artificially ingraven, and two doozen of Spoones were preſented to Duke
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:25768:45"/>
                  <hi>Bernhard,</hi> famous for 20 rich and ſumptuous Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and laſtly for the goodly church and tower of curious ſtone.</p>
               <p>The conditions concluded at the ſurrendry (which I would not have rehearſed but upon the occaſion following) were theſe, That all the Prieſts ſhould march away with the commander, officers and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. That no Burger of what quality ſoever ſhould depart. That thoſe which went away ſhould have a convoy of horſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The breach of the ſecond article had like to have expoſed all to the conquerors mercy: A rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant was found in the waggons, and thereupon the convoy pillaged them, and brought both him and the reſt backe as priſoners to <hi>Fryburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus captain <hi>Iohn Scot</hi> relates this accident: but a letter directed to <hi>Rhinacker</hi> from duke <hi>Bernh.</hi> (the copy whereof I have ſeen both in French &amp; Dutch) expreſſeth more: take it thus abſtracted:</p>
               <p>Yours, dated at <hi>Briſack,</hi> April 6, 16. I have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; wherein you complaine of an abuſe done to the garriſon of <hi>Freyburg</hi> at their departure, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a releaſe of the priſoners belonging to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment. A copy of the accord I have ſent you here incloſed, by which you may perceive that Colonel <hi>Eſher</hi> the late Governor there brake it in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; firſt becauſe in the articles he had no colours and ſtandards, yet he cauſed four to be caried away before the garriſon. Secondly, the garriſon ſhould not pillage the towne, yet he tooke away the townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens horſes, plundered the cloyſters, and mounted the cavalliers which wanted horſes, upon the Burg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:25768:46"/>beaſts. Thirdly, their deſire to carry away ſome cattell, was expugned and denied by us, yet they attempted to drive away many. Fourthly, That ſuch as had run away from our army with their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and armes, ſhould abide therein: yet contrary to the accord, they were not onely concealed in the waggons, their cloathes being changed, and ſhuffled away over the wall, but the Imperialliſts got upon their horſes and would have ſtollen them away, and this cauſed a broile betwixt the convoy and the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and the reducement of the Caeſarians to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</p>
               <p>It was a faire anſwer, and reliſhed as much of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary juſtice, as his after act did of grace; he ſet them at liberty without ranſom, meekly blaming the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy, and adviſing <hi>Eſcher</hi> to uſe more ſincerity in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the tearmes of capitulation.</p>
               <p>The city was wonne, and now hee adviſeth how to keepe it: firſt hee layd into it the red Regiment, with one captaine and officer of each company; but having notice that the enemy with a powerful army was comming to furniſh <hi>Briſack</hi> (at which hee had an emulous eye) with victuals, he removed the Red Regiment, and appointed <hi>Karosky</hi> to that province, with a regiment of horſe to ſcour the waies betwixt <hi>Fryburg</hi> and <hi>Briſack;</hi> and another of foot to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the city. And now to omit his ſeverall Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings and diſcampings, which may puzzle, cannot pleaſe the Reader, we will ſet downe his and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers actions till his battell with <hi>Goetz</hi> the Generall of the Caeſarian and Bavarian forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Kanofsky</hi> having according to the dukes directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:25768:46"/>commanded out a party towards <hi>Briſack,</hi>
                  <note n="5" place="margin">regiments of <hi>Butlers</hi> Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery defeated by <hi>Kanoſsky.</hi>
                  </note> ſixe of his cavalliers ſpurring up before the avantgard, fell upon the place where our Iriſh <hi>Butler,</hi> newly come from the French County, lay with his Infantery, conſiſting of fifteen hundred men divided into 5 re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, lay intrenched neer <hi>Briſack.</hi> The governor <hi>Rhinacker</hi> for want of proviſions being unwilling to entertaine them, they had thought to have amaſed them by a ſudden alarme, and unexpectedly to have ſurpriſed them; but the project failed, that place did not give them hope of glory, but miniſtred cauſe of feare. Yet their moderation crowned them with a victory, whoſe raſhneſſe might have brought them not to loſſe onely but ignominy. The Imperialliſts kept a good watch, were upon their gard, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the adventurers to fly ſo affrightedly, that their countenances diſcovering their hearts, the whole vantgard was poſſeſſed with the ſame cold paſſion, and all the other cavalliers. The troupes of <hi>Kanof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skies</hi> horſe were then upon a coſſe-way, hemmed in on both ſides with Mooraſſe, not able to turn to the right hand or left: there was only one way for their ſafety, which was with their faces about to return as ſoone as might be. This courſe they tooke, and the Caeſarians ſuppoſing them to fly cowardly, purſued them eagerly, till having field roome, and being not confined by the Mooraſſes, they changed their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and aſſaulting their enemies unexpectedly, they flew three hundred of them, and took no more than 26 priſoners (amongſt which were two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, 3 lievtenants and one enſigne) for they would give no quarter to any but this ſmall number.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:25768:47"/>
Generall Major <hi>Tupadel</hi> about the ſame time had ſent out a party after ſome Caeſarians,
<note place="margin">120 Cuiraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers ſurpriſed by <hi>Tupadel.</hi>
                  </note> but miſſing them they re-incountred with 30 cuiraſſiers neere <hi>Aurach</hi> in the dukedome of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fled, and were ſo purſued that the <hi>Saxons</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces entred with them into <hi>Aurach</hi> ſo ſuddenly, that they tooke the towne before the reſt of the garriſon (being an hundred cuiraſſiers, whom they put to the ſword) could have notice of their entry, or betake themſelves to the caſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roza</hi> at the ſame preſent was as active and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as either of them: he ſent abroad 300 horſe of his owne Regiment to deſcry the enemy, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his poſture; who firſt met with 80 crabats, the major part whereof fell by the ſword (that Nation ſeldome giving or deſiring quarter) and the reſt were taken priſoners, by whom hee was informed, that another party followed him, conſiſting of 120 cuiraſſiers:
<note place="margin">200 Crabats and 6 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons ſlain and taken by <hi>Roſa.</hi>
                  </note> the certaine place where they lay was ſhewed him, and thither hee poſted in ſpeed, ſlew ſome and defeated the reſt: and being informed by his priſoners, that eighty of their comrades were at <hi>Altkirken,</hi> an Imperiall towne in the dukedome of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> to conduct ſixe companies of Dragons, with their ſtandards and baggage to the Barbarian Rendezvous neer <hi>Nordlingen;</hi> he placed an ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cado for them, attended their comming foure and twenty houres, when ſeeing them upon their march they charged them ſo roundly, they they ſlew the moſt of them, gained all their baggage, amongſt which were two carvaches and four ſtandards. The Major which commanded the regiment (their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:25768:47"/>
                  <hi>Wolfe</hi> being ſlain at the firſt battell neer <hi>Rhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felden</hi>) eſcaped with much adoe, beeing ſhot twice acroſſe the body. The Lievtenant Colonel and all the officers became priſoners of war, and <hi>Roſa</hi> by this happy occaſion maſter of <hi>Altkirken,</hi> where hee refreſhed his Dragons, and reinforced his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with a new accrewt of 400 men, as did alſo moſt of his highneſſes Colonells about the ſame time.</p>
               <p>Theſe checks the Imperiall and Bavarian Armies received before the battell;
<note place="margin">Altkirken ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in.</note> which much abated their number, whileſt the Saxon Dukes forces en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, a new ſupply both of men and victuals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought him out of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Elſas Savern</hi> by the Count <hi>de Guebriant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many cares attend him which enjoyeth much.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Io. de Werth</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved into France.</note> The Duke had now two things which required his vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant eye, the ſafe keeping of his priſoners, <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> and <hi>Erkenfourt,</hi> and the anticipating of <hi>Goetz</hi> for his intended victualling of <hi>Briſack.</hi> The firſt the Chriſtian King tooke from him, by ſending for the priſoners and carrying them to <hi>Boys S. Vincents,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant about three leagues from <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other burthen lay upon the Dukes ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who in the end of May underſtanding that <hi>Goetz</hi> lay incamped neere <hi>Rothywel</hi> and <hi>Villinguer,</hi> marched thitherward with foure great Cannons, twelve field pieces, nine thouſand foot and foure thouſand horſe, to give him battell. But <hi>Goetz,</hi> who labored more to revictual <hi>Briſack</hi> before the battell, than after, being advertiſed of his march, diſcam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped preſently, and removed to the <hi>Schwartz-Waldt,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:25768:48"/>that he might more covertly performe his task, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his proviſions through the valley of <hi>Kintzin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen</hi> and towne of <hi>Offemburgh.</hi> And at that time hee relieved the Briſackers with corne enough for 4 or five dayes and no more; only 150 of his Cavalliers entring into the towne, each with a bag of meal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him. <hi>Goetz</hi> himſelfe ſtill delining the battell, and ſhifting from place to place, one part of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall army taking its way toward <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther following their Generall toward <hi>Hailbrunne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Saxon duke was buſie all Iune in ſeeking his enemy,
<note place="margin">400 Crabats ſlain &amp; routed by D. <hi>Serub.</hi>
                  </note> but could not find him, but was in danger to have been found himſelfe by 400 crabats, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advertiſed that the Duke was lodged in a ſmall village named <hi>Brombach,</hi> with a ſmall retinue, thought to have ſurpriſed his perſon. But the Duke was not ignorant of their deſigne, and ſending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently to the groſſe of his army, which was not far off, his ſuccours came in ſo opportunely, that he ſurrounded the wood where the crabats lurked, put 200 of them to the ſword, and routed the reſt utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The enemy not yet appearing, the Swedes made an inrode into the Blacke forreſt, and at one time brought to the campe 1000 oxen, which the duke cauſed to be fed in the medows for his uſe.</p>
               <p>But at length the oppoſite armies met and joined battell, Iuly 9 new ſtile, wherin the duke was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a glorious victory. The particulars where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of becauſe they fall not within the preſcribed time for this hiſtory, I ſhall referre to another diſcovery, wherin our Swediſh <hi>Fabius Bannier,</hi> who hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blowes ruined the great Imperial and Saxon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:25768:48"/>and the reſt of thoſe Heroes, whoſe worthy acts are not here expreſſed, ſhall be remembred at large, and have their hiſtory continued to this preſent day.</p>
               <p>Here I would make a concluding period, but the ſiege of <hi>Fontarabie</hi> muſt have an abortive birth in the relation, as it had a prodigious end in the action.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:25768:49"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The ſiege of</hi> Fontarabie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow uncertain the iſſues of War be, if there were no other Example left, this ſtory alone, might ſufficiently teſtifie: never was Expedition under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken more cheerfully, the Nobles and Gentry of <hi>Guienne,</hi> and the South of <hi>France,</hi> engaging themſelves therin voluntarily, never was an adventure made more gloriouſly, begunne more auſpiciouſly, nor continued more fortunately, till the laſt Act, and yet there is ſcarce a Record of any which ended more fearfully.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> appointed by the Chriſtian King as Generall, accompanied with the Dukes <hi>d' Eſpernon, de Valette de S. Simon,</hi> the Marques <hi>de la Force</hi> &amp; other men of eminent note, 18000 foot &amp; 7000 horſe, was to attend this buſineſſe by land, and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> with a good Navy by Sea, the Coaſt of <hi>Provence</hi> committed to the ſole care of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:25768:49"/>the Earle of <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> and the Archbiſhoprick not engaged therin:
<note place="margin">Two Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerks men of War taken at <hi>Port du paſſage.</hi>
               </note> Fortune at firſt attended them both by Sea and land, the Admirall, <hi>Iune</hi> 30. <hi>Iuly</hi> 10, took two <hi>Dunkerkers</hi> men of War, tranſporting of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to the Port <hi>du Paſſage,</hi> kept the Bottomes for the King his Maſters ſervice, and ſent the priſoners, to <hi>Bayon.</hi> The Prince before that day had removed all the <hi>Remora's</hi> which might hinder him, taken in <hi>Iron, Viarſon, Renteria, Loys,</hi> the <hi>Port du paſſage,
<note place="margin">Divers places taken by the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi>
                  </note> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> the Caſtle upon the Harbour, where hee moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Cannon, and began to play upon the Town, <hi>Iuly</hi> 3, new ſtile, which ſtrook off a Pinacle from the Caſtle, and beat downe ſome houſes, and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſent a Trumpet to ſummon <hi>Bechare</hi> the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Towne in the Valley of <hi>Seringueville,</hi> he began his approches and Earthen Fortifications. The Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons and Inhabitants tugged with death, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to hinder their entrenching, but could not: <hi>Iuly</hi> 10 new ſtile, they ſallyed forth upon the Pioners, and ſpent foure vollyes of Cannon ſhot upon the Campe, but were forced to retire. The next day there iſſued through the <hi>Sally-port,</hi> 100 men well ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in battell array, ſeconded by as many others with Pick-axes and Spades to rayſe the Trenches, but were ſurprized by a Regiment of <hi>French,</hi> whoſe charge was to guard the labourers: who ſlew above 120 of them, and wounded many others, conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as many as could to fly in a diſorderly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bechare</hi> thus ſummoned,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bechare</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, &amp; not yielding.</note> the inhabitans ſent a a Drum to the Prince, <hi>Iuly</hi> 4, 14. to tell him that they had order from their Vice-roy, to mayntayne the Town for the Catholike King, and that they
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:25768:50"/>hourly expected the ſuccours which hee had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, His Excellency being fully reſolved to relieve them. The Prince incenſed with this anſwer, gave order inſtantly to the Duke <hi>De Saint Simon,</hi> to draw 1000 foot, and ſix Cornets of horſe, out of the body of the Regiments,
<note place="margin">The Duke <hi>de S. Simon</hi> hath order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it.</note> and with thoſe troups, and one piece of Cannon to compell them, giving leave to the Souldiers to uſe them with all hoſtility, that they might be exemplary to others.</p>
            <p>The next day, <hi>Iuly</hi> 5, 15. the Duke Saint <hi>Simon,</hi> marched from <hi>Iron,</hi> with his deſigned troups of Horſe and Foot, theſe being commanded by <hi>Marin an Aide de Campe, Mun, Bevidu, Beaupuy,</hi> and <hi>Merin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> Camp-maſters, and encamped at <hi>Sarra</hi> the laſt Town of <hi>France,</hi> where hee met with <hi>Amon</hi> Grand Bayliffe of the Country <hi>de Labour,</hi> who preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him with 300 Baſques ready for his ſervice. Here, by adviſe of the Counſell of Warre, hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Amon</hi> to ſurveigh the ways, and make them fit for the portage of his Cannon, furniſhing the Baſques with Axes, and other tools for that ſervice, and then himſelfe, with the Army marched after them.</p>
            <p>No Enemy, which could oppoſe him, was yet expected,
<note place="margin">Encounters 1200 Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</note> yet it was ſuſpected, that ſuch an one there might be, and <hi>Marine</hi> with a 100 foot Perdu's, was ſent to ſee if any ſuch appeared. He had ſcarce tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled half a league upon the Spaniſh ground, but he ſpied two Battalions of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> upon a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Eſtward from <hi>Bechara,</hi> prepared to fight, as hee judged, by their orderly march and ſhouts, like thoſe which are uſuall when battels joyne. Nor did his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:25768:50"/>conjecture faile him; a ſelected party drawn out of the Spaniſh body, which conſiſted of 1200 men, came up to him roundly, charged upon him furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and were received bravely, and after them fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Groſſe of the Army, which had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſurprized him, had not the Duke <hi>de</hi> S. <hi>Simon</hi> come in happily to his Reſcue. And here began an hot fight, wherein the Commanders of both ſides ſhewed both courage and dexterity,
<note place="margin">Defeats them.</note> yet in the end came off with victory, and though the Infantry was tired, and ſome of their Cavallary, as well as of the Spaniſh ſlaine, they forced the Foe to flie over the Mountains, where (not knowing the wayes) which of themſelves are rough and uncouth, they could not follow them. This brunt being paſt, 200 of his Baſques were ſent to burn and pillage <hi>Bechara,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Burneth <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chara.</hi>
               </note> which they did ſo expeditiouſly, that in foure houres ſpace the Town was burnt to aſhes, maugre the reſiſtance of the inhabitants, &amp; 300 <hi>Caſtilians,</hi> which laboured to preſerve it, though theſe laſt were martiall men drawn out of the old Bands, and the Nobility of the Frontier Towns. The Duke thus rid of the Spaniſh forces, and ſufficiently avenged of <hi>Bechara,</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Rally up his forces, and purſue the late Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into the Valley of <hi>Saque,</hi> but underſtanding that the Grand Prior of Navarre was at Saint <hi>Eſtefe,</hi> but half a league off with 3000 men, hee changed his minde and marched to <hi>Challar</hi> and <hi>Sourgaramourdi,</hi> where he ſummoned the inhabitants which came in, ſupplyed him with victuals, promiſed obedience to the Chriſtian King, and aſſured him that they of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> had burned the Magazin, which the Grand
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:25768:51"/>Prior of <hi>Navarre,</hi> had erected there, for the mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his forces, and ſo returned to Sarra.</p>
            <p>The Duke was no ſooner diſengaged of his charge abroad, but the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was ingaged in another at the Campe before <hi>Fontarabie,</hi> or <hi>Fuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Rabia.</hi> Three thouſand Spaniards were brought from Saint <hi>Sebaſtians</hi> by Sea in Pinnaſſes and Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops, and landed at the Port <hi>du paſſage,</hi> but covered from the Garriſons eye by a Mountain betwixt the Sea and them, their intention being to regaine the place, as appeared afterwards by an <hi>Adviſo</hi> found about their Commander from <hi>Madrid,</hi> wherin hee was enjoyned to recover it, if it were poſſible, and to aſſault it,
<note place="margin">3000 <hi>Spaniards</hi> defeated neere <hi>Fontaraby.</hi>
               </note> in what ſtate ſoever he found it: It was a deſperate attempt, ſo neer an Army Royall, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture with ſo few men upon a place of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, nor was the Chieftain inſenfible of it, his moſt familiar friend, confeſſing after the French vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, that upon the march, hee rounded him in the eare, ſaying, we march to our death; yet this taske was enjoyned him, and he to ſhew his loyalty to his King and Country undertook. But though the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt was deſperate, it was not unpoſſible, hee might perhaps have attained his end, if hee had not been diſcovered by 200 Saylours, which were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> to mend the Veſſels lately taken from the Dunkerkers, who perceiving them climbe the Hill as they were at work, fled preſently, and were purſued to the Barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadoes of the Campe, which theſe Spaniſh troups aſſaulted in ſeven places, till the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> who was there in perſon, drew his forces together
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:25768:51"/>which changing theſe Adventurers home ſlue 11 of their Officers, above 600 common men, wounded their Chieftain, and took him priſoner, forced the reſt to uſe their heels, &amp; purſued them to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Cliffs of Saint <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this fight by land another happened by Sea, where the Sea-men ſped no better then their Land-men: ſix Spaniſh Pionaſſes,
<note place="margin">And two Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſhips ſunk</note> and 12 Veſſels of burthen fell upon eight ſhips, which the French ſtill kept before <hi>Fontaraby;</hi> but after a fight of 2 houres, two of the biggeſt Spaniſh Bottoms being ſunk, the reſt hoyſed ſaile, and with the helpe of a faire winde recovered Saint <hi>Sebaſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince by this found no oppoſition abroad, he had free liberty, and freely uſed it, to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſiege, wherby hee brought the Town to extreme neceſſity, but how ſucceſſefull the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe was, though the French will not, a Spaniſh Capuchin, by his Relation penned modeſtly, like an Hiſtorian, though with ſome interlarded ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and printed at <hi>Madrid, Sept.</hi> 2, 12 will inform you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:52"/>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:25768:52"/>
            <head>The Siege of <hi>Fontaraby</hi> raiſed.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>A Relation written from the Campe by Father Fryer</hi> Francis <hi>of</hi> Tarrazona, <hi>Reader of the Arts in the Convent of</hi> Capuchins <hi>of</hi> Pampelona, <hi>vnto Father</hi> Guardian <hi>of the</hi> Capuchnis <hi>of the Convent of</hi> Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoſa.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ather <hi>Guardian.</hi> Seeing that the receipts of benefits are the pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of thankfulneſſe, it could not ſeeme juſt in me if I ſhould omit to amplifie my thankfulneſſe to your Paternity by not declaring and imparting unto your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo ſingular a bleſſing, and ſo ful of divine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as was our late Victory whereof I have been an eye-witneſſe and now ſhall make a plaine narration without complements, addreſſing my ſelfe to truth only, which ſhall be ſufficient to incite your Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to exerciſe your devotion in a ſerious and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate thankſgiving. The great ſtrait and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in which the French held the ſtrong Towne of <hi>Fontaraby</hi> is not unknowne to your Paternity, and how our Councell of Warre had reſolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it ſo ſoone as ſufficient forces might be raiſed to encounter with ſo great an Enemy though the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution was moſt dangerous. Vpon Tueſday <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 21/31. the Lord Admirall of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Veles</hi> Generals of the Forces of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:25768:53"/>
               <hi>Guiapuſcoa</hi> reſolved to releeve it, their Army conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of 16000 Foot and 600 Horſe, which to that purpoſe being devided into 3 Squadrons, the Lords Generals with the groſſe of the Army marched to the deſcent of a hill which is ſcituated and runneth from the gate of the paſſage unto the Fort, and there mounted 8. Pieces of Artillery in the place where the Marquis of <hi>Mirtaca</hi> was enquartered with the third part of the <hi>Conde</hi> Dukes Army and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> forces. By the deſcent of the valley the Marquis of <hi>Torrecuſa</hi> marched with a good Squadron of Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and <hi>Don Piedro Giron</hi> with 2000 Foot marched towards <hi>Irun</hi> where the Enemy was fortified. In this poſture was the Army the 20/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> with purpoſe to relieve the beſieged the next day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by 4 of the clock in the morning: But it pleaſed the Almighty (not without a myſtery as it appeared afterwards) to fruſtrate their reſolutions by this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. The night following was tempeſtuous with Lightning and thunder, and the clouds diſſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to raine which fell without intermiſſion the ſpace of five dayes: The valley was bare of wood and trees, and neere the Sea, and the toilſomneſſe of that night is inexpreſſible, our travell ſo much increaſing that we could not ſecure our lodgings nor make Barraca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, but for want of wood we were forced to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe, the Generals compaſſionating the Soldiers licenſing them to retire and refreſh themſelves in the places next adjoyning.</p>
            <p>The Lord Admirall and the Marquis of <hi>Veles</hi> were in the Sally from Munday to Friday, when the raine
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:25768:53"/>not ceaſing and the waters deſcending to a place cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Tezo</hi> they commanded the Artillery to retire, that the Soldiers leaving their Tents in good order might be refreſhed: By which meanes the valley became ſo deſolate, that they much feared the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my would ſalley forth upon thoſe which remained behind thus harazzed and wearied with the rigour and extreamity of the weather.</p>
            <p>The foulneſſe of the weather overjoyed the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which thence concluded, that God aſſiſted them againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> arming the Heavens to croſſe their intentions: and to this purpoſe, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſent a Cartell to the Governor of <hi>Fontarabie,</hi> the ſumme whereof was, That to ſhew himſelfe a mercifull and Catholick Prince hee adviſed him to render the place, offering him that honorable Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which could no wayes impeach his Honor who had ſo long maintained the place, and ſo valiantly, and that the rather becauſe all hope of ſuccours was now taken from him, the Generals being already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired: and that hee was not ignorant of his want of Soldiers, ammunition, and Victuals, by which the beſieged ſhould be enforced to yeeld: which if they refuſed to doe of their owne accord, they would be expoſed to the edge of the Sword, the Commander ſhould be made ſhorter by the head, and the reſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſuch cruelties as happen in caſes of aſſault, the Officers not being able (though willing) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the fury of their Soldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Doming Leguia</hi> a Knight of <hi>Biſcay</hi> then Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Fontarabie,</hi> anſwered well in the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:25768:54"/>of a great Souldier, as the Gentilizza of a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, approving the adviſe, and returning due thankes for the offered curteſie and counſell: but in the point of impoſſibility of ſuccours hee was not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harted there being noneceſſity thereof, nor himſelfe being leſſe confident to keepe the place then he was before, being already provided and abundantly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of all things whereof his Excellency ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be deſtitute, and for the point of looſing his Head, hee was confident no ſuch diſaſter could befall him, reſolving rather to dye like a valiant Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, then to become a Priſoner and have his head cut off, and what hee believed impoſſible to winne he had no cauſe to feare, his praeſidiarie Soldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolved to oppoſe the valour of the Beſiegers.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> being moved with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, cauſed 3 aſſaults to be made, in which divers of the French were ſlaine, and vpon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 4. of <hi>September</hi> New ſtile, they advanced ſo farre as within 30 foote of the height of the wall, but they were all ſlaine two excepted, which infected thoſe which ſhould have beaten them on and ſeconded them, with ſuch a contagion of feare, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare to aſſault the Gariſon.</p>
            <p>The Admirall the Archbiſhop of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with 30 other Biſhops came thither alſo, who hindred the importation of any ſuccors into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by Sea: and hee ſeeing the place not ſurrendred after ſo many aſſaults, told the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> that he appear'd an unexperienced Souldier, to make ſo many aſſaults from the Baletta with ſo ſmall repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:25768:54"/>intimating that he would have the place aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted vpon the Birth of our Lady, by 4 of the clocke in the morning, but the Prince oppoſed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Arch-biſhop was Generall at Sea, and that it did not concerne him to intermeddle with the affaires by Land. Hereupon enſued more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention occaſioned by the Duke, and <hi>d' Eſpernon</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the Archbiſhop: and vpon the overture the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> haſted to renew the aſſault for the reſpect he gaue the Archbiſhop: but his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe entring into a more ſerious conſideration, and judging (not without reaſon) of the various events of Warre, eſpecially our men being couragious, and well fortified, intending to diſingage himſelfe from the obligation wherin he was involved, in an angry moode replyed to the Archbiſhop, that being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall at Sea it did not concern him to giue the aſſault by Land, and that he would not looſe the glory of the aſſault which properly belonged to his place. To appeaſe all, his Highneſſe prepared a mine which he intended to ſpring vpon the Vigill of our Lady, and placed therein 29. barrels of Gun-powder, by which no doubt a great part of the wall would haue fallen, it being torne by other mines and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries: To effect it the Archbiſhop commanded out the ableſt Souldiours in the Nauy, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed 4000 Doblons ſhould be deſtributed amongſt the adventurous which ſhould firſt make the aſſault the moſt couragiouſly and readily. The aſſault was made in 4 places, the French being confident that the Towne would be rendered when the mine was
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:25768:55"/>ſprung by reaſon the defendants were but few, and they grew weary by toyle and unable to hinder their approaches.</p>
            <p>Hitherto God was pleaſed that wee ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but vpon <hi>Sunday</hi> at 5. of the clocke the raine cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the weather holding vp, our Generals pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all their forces in the ſame poſture wherin they had beene formerly ranged a League from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Vpon <hi>Munday</hi> at night the Generals aſſembled at the place called <hi>Lezo,</hi> deſirous to ſuccour the Towne with all expedition, for the day before ſome ſallied out of it, to certifie them that if they were not relieved within 3 dayes the French would bee Maſters thereof: and thereupon they reſolved to aſſayle the Enemies vpon <hi>Tueſday</hi> the Vigill of our Lady.</p>
            <p>The time did not then ſerve to muſter the forces, but it is ſuppoſed that 3000 were loſt by the deluge of raine and waters. Vpon <hi>Tueſday</hi> in the morning the troopes were devided into 3. ſquadrons. By the deſcent of the hil which runneth from the paſſage to the City was the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mortara</hi> with 2000 of the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke, the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and others, 1000 <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varrois,</hi> and <hi>Provincials,</hi> who were ſo ordered and quartered, that the right wing of the <hi>Vantguard</hi> ſhould conſiſt of a third part of the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke his Regiment. The Battaile and Reare ſhould take vp the other people amounting in all to 4000 with ſome Companies of Horſe.</p>
            <p>At the loweſt part of the hill to the Southward lay the Lord Admirall of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and the Marqueſſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:25768:55"/>of <hi>Veles</hi> with the groſſe of the Army, with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Campe Generall the Marqueſſe of <hi>Torre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſa</hi> with 2000 ſelected and choyſe Souldiours of <hi>Don Fauſto de Ludioſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ableſt Souldiours were diſpoſed in the moſt eminent places, that the Enemy might not bee able to cut off our forces. On the other ſide of <hi>Irun</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Don Pedro Giron</hi> with 2000 men, the moſt of them <hi>Caſtilians</hi> with the Campe-maſter <hi>Sebaſtian Granero</hi> Generall of the Artillery, and a troope of Horſe to poſſeſſe the moſt eminent places about <hi>Irun,</hi> and to hinder the ſuccours which might come from any of the French Quarters at <hi>Fontarabie.</hi> We that were Capuchns devided our ſelves into 4 parts diſtributing our ſelves with our companies of the Religious which were then there.</p>
            <p>In this poſture we advanced towards the Enemy in front the ſame day by 4 of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mortara</hi> immediately gayned the aſcent of the hill whereof hee had beene Maſter before but had then willingly abandoned, and now compaſſing the little hill above, he gayned the eminent places untill he approched within Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket ſhot of the Enemies trenches, from whence hee received ſome round charges. The Horſe and <hi>Iriſh</hi> wheeled to the left hand towards the Sea to ſecure themſelves from the offence of the Enemy which lay behind the hill.</p>
            <p>The Marquis of <hi>Torrecuſa</hi> immediatly ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſecure place below the Hill, after hee had gained two Quarters from the Enemy over againſt a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:25768:56"/>Redoubt ſcituated at the end of the Trench, which was the greateſt Fortification the Enemy had. His troopes immediatly aſſaulted their Enemies, ſome with Pikes, others with Sword and Target, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with Muskets, which brake into a troope of <hi>French</hi> Horſe, forcing them twice to recoyle: But the Camp-Maſter Generall drawing up the Corſlets cauſed his Companies to renew their charges, and joyning their Musketiers together, they charged the Enemy ſo forcibly that he was not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the aſſault, but gaue ground.</p>
            <p>In this firſt encounter foure or 6 men entred the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt fighting like Lyons, but the Enemy overmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them in number enforced them to retire. But wee returned with ſuch fury to the aſſault of the Redoubt, that having killed many French wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayned the place at the very point of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and though they were many and well defended with artificiall and intricate trenches, and a ditch of very great depth, yet they abandoned the place.</p>
            <p>The Enemies Campe removed it ſelfe a Musket ſhot, the Horſe before, and the Foote behind: where they ſtood amazed whilſt you will repeate the Creed 6 times, determining as farre as wee could perceiue to beate us backe, driving them back out of the Redoubt, and aſſaulting us by troopes. But our men being Maſters of the place grew ſo couragious-inſtant,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:25768:56"/>they charged them ſo roundly, that they were enforced to turne their backes with much loſſe at one inſtant, none of the <hi>French</hi> appearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue in their Trenches, but leauing many dead therein, and ſome Canons of a middle ſize wherewith they had much endamaged us, Our forces followed the chaſe. Some of the Enemies that is the Cavallary flying towards <hi>Iran,</hi> other towards the Sea, the moſt whereof were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Tide running with great force and more then ordinary becauſe of the Land waters: wee flew many of them when they were up to the middle in water, when they who had entered the ſmall Boates and could not row againſt the Tide rendred themſelves, and with folded hands and mournfull voices, cryed <hi>Vive le Roy de Eſpagne,</hi> God quarter for Gods ſake: Our Companies haſtned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea in extreame danger to the judgement of all beholders to doe our Chriſtian duties in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the afflicted, and it was our great good hap, that in ſo great hazard wherein wee were involved our people having leſſe reſiſtance then the poore French, wee exerciſed our Charity to the comfort of thoſe that were at the point of death. Thoſe which fled towards <hi>Iran</hi> wee could not purſue, but if wee had but ſtopped their way onely with 200 Muſquetiers, without doubt they had beene all cut in peeces or become our Priſoners, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to fore-ſee, we not imagining to have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo notable a Victory, our counſels onely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:25768:57"/>to relieue the Port, not ſuſpecting that ſo puiſſant an Enemy, ſo well fortified in his Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches would ſo ſoone turne his backe, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them drowned themſelves in the paſſage of <hi>Bobia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe of <hi>Fontarabie</hi> could not ſalley forth, being reduced to ſo ſmall a number, which nevertheleſſe if they had done, no doubt they had made a very great ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>Our Generals met together about 5. of the clock in the afternoone, and entred <hi>Fontarabie,</hi> where they were received with incredible joy by a people which that day and before had endured ſo many broyles and toyles, and had ſpent all the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in viewing the Hills a farre off, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the expected ſuccours would come; and were almoſt paſt hope, becauſe they could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry no part of them.</p>
            <p>The Lords Generals, like moſt devout Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Princes, went inſtantly to expreſſe their pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acknowledgement of ſo graat a Victory, and ſang <hi>Te Deum,</hi> which though it was not atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the greater Muſicke, was done with greater Zeale and affection, Drummes, Trumpets, and Artillery, beeing not neceſſary for ſuch a Solemnity.</p>
            <p>Their devotions ended, the Lords Generals,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:25768:57"/>ſaluted the inhabitants with moſt loving embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thanking them in the name of his Catholike Majeſty, for their conſtant Loyalty, by which they had pleaſed God, and defended their King, and Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Pedro de Giron</hi> had order to make no aſſault vpon the <hi>French</hi> Campe, till 4 of the clocke in the morning of our Lady Day, but the Enemy fled that Night, and concealed his flight by many falſe fires. They left behind them much warlike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, ammunition apparell and riches, not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the baggage as they intended, and <hi>Don Pedro</hi> might without reſiſtance have poſſeſſed himſelfe of <hi>Iran</hi> in the morning if hee had followed it.</p>
            <p>Hee that did beſt for gayning this victory, was the Marqueſſe <hi>De Torrecuſa,</hi> with the <hi>Navarroyes</hi> and <hi>Neapolitans.</hi> Concerning the Particular Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallieres I can ſay little moſt of them beeing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to mee. Some affirme, that <hi>Don Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco de Garro</hi> was the firſt, which entred into the Enemies Trenches, other ſay the Earle of <hi>Xaviers</hi> though he was beaten out againe by the blow of an Halbert, which had undoubtedly ſlaine him had not his Gorget ſaved him. Captaine <hi>Pedro de Mara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidis</hi> Knight of the order of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> entred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo into the ſame Redoubt, whence he brought away a <hi>French</hi> Colours having ſlaine the Enſigne in ſight of the whole Army, others report the ficſt that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:25768:58"/>to have beene <hi>Don Iuan D' Eques</hi> a Knight of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and that a <hi>Neapolitane</hi> of <hi>Valentia</hi> charged very brauely.</p>
            <p>There were ſlaine of the <hi>French</hi> 1200, which were ſeene floating upon the Son, moſt of them men of quality as it ſeemeth by their outward Habit; wee loſt not many, the generall vote is not above thirty, yet the Lord Admirall ſaith more, nor had we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wounded. The Priſoners taken that day were above 1000. and the number increaſeth daily, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which had hid themſelves in Brakes and Thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, being compelled abroad by Hunger. It is ſaid, there were 50 of the French Nobility wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; but that is ſcarce credible. A French Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet came into our Army the Friday following, who affirmed, they had loſt 6 thouſand men: and being demanded what the French conceived of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, hee anſwered; the Spaniſh are Couragious, and the French want Government: which hee meant perhaps of thoſe which betrayed the Cauſe by their feare and flight; for they could not bee ignorant, that their Forces then conſiſted of two and twenty thouſand Foot, 1000 Horſe, fifty good Ships well provided, and that a re-enforcement of 6000 men was expected daily from <hi>Baiona:</hi> the Spaniſh Army conſiſting onely of 3000 Foot, and five hundred Horſe, more or leſſe, and the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being fortified, and wee having no place of ſtrength, how could ſo ſhamefull a flight, and ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:25768:58"/>glorious a Victory bee expected? The Booty was great, and the pillage was increaſed, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy vainely conceiving (according to the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Capuchin priſoner) to winne ground upon <hi>Fontarabie,</hi> and then to fall upon St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> a place of leſſe importance, and ſo to paſſe victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly throughout all <hi>Spaine</hi> even to <hi>Madrill</hi> without reſiſtance, which was alſo beleeved by them as a matter of faith.</p>
            <p>They came to the Siege very rich in Plate, Gold, coſtly Lodgings, Pavillions very curiouſly wrought, Cabinets, and other precious furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Wee ſeized the Wardrobe of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> wherein wee found much and very rich enamelled Plate, and a moſt rich Enſigne of the Order, which was of ſuch eſtimation, that the next day hee ſent a Trumpeter to the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> intreating him to returne the Plate and the Golden Fleece and hee would allow the true worth thereof for the ſame. The Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> wardrobe alſo they ſeized, and part of his owne wearing Apparell, and the foure thouſand <hi>Doublous</hi> which hee promiſed to deliver amongſt his Souldiers, to encourage them to the aſſault.</p>
            <p>It is thought hee was preſent in the Campe at the time of the skirmiſh, and it is not knowne how hee eſcaped. Becauſe hee falls not downe towards the Sea, it is thought hee betooke himſelfe to the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:25768:59"/>Cittadell of Saint <hi>Elmo,</hi> from whence the next day it was obſerved the <hi>French</hi> vayled their ſayles ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given fire to their Cittadell, cloyed it with Artillery. Their Muskets, Harquebuſes, and Pikes were all left in the place being too heauy to beare away and might hinder their eſcape. Their caſſocks of Skarlet, and other of fineſt cloth with the orders of the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt</hi> were very many. One of our Souldiours had 3 of them, and ſold one for 16. Royals which was then worth 100 Duckets. The hangings were of unſhorne greene Velvet broy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Gold, emboſſed with Iewels, and tufted with greene water Grograynes, buttons of gold and rich galownes. The Iewels, chaines, watches, and many other rich ornaments, were found vpon the dead bodies in the Sea. In ſuch Fiſhings the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were very skilfull diving under the waters to find them.</p>
            <p>The Enſignes gained from the enemy were about a hundred, though the Admirall had not ſo many, many of them were in the hands of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, deſirous to place them in their ſeverall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, as Trophies of their Victory: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the old ſouldiers made no account of them, ſaying, they would only place in their Countreyes thoſe which were taken and wonne from the hands of the enemy. The pieces of Artillery which were left, during the Siege, were 23, and many of them Spaniſh, with the Armes and Names of the Kings
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:25768:59"/>of <hi>Spaine:</hi> others affirme that there were many more left, they left there alſo many barrels of powder, and about three hundred <hi>Granadoes,</hi> which made ſuch ſpoyle within <hi>Fontarabie;</hi> It is a divel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh invention, an inſtrument of warre, weying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 150 pounds of <hi>Caſtile</hi> Iron, three fingers thick, with a narrow mouth, faſtened with knots, cimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with toe, and this knot lying higher, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is moiſtned and wet, that it may continue a time in the Aire, before the report, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards recoyleth from the mouth, which penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an houſe, though it hath five floores, it will paſſe through them all, and pierce through the whole edifice, and hath left the Bullet, which is a little Morter, with a large mouth, like the <hi>Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> but narrow on the contrary extremity. It is reported they coſt 70 Duckets a piece.</p>
            <p>The morning before the battell arrived to the French, 4 or 5 Pinnaces, loaden with White-meates, Wine, Sweet-meates, daynties, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary proviſion, all which was left in the Field, and gave our Army good refreſhment. In one of the Pinnaces were 6 pieces of Ordnance, and amongſt them one curious piece belonging to the Cardinall <hi>Richeleau.</hi> The Fleete was onely in want of men, moſt of them leaving the Sea, to give the aſſault by land, and it remaining at ſea, till the day of our
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:25768:60"/>Ladies Birth, without a convenient tide, if there we had had but a ſmall Army by ſea, we had gained that alſo.</p>
            <p>The Forts and Walls of <hi>Fontaraby,</hi> were much ruinated, eſpecially a Curtaine called the Queenes, which looked towards the Mountaine, which being broken by twelve Mines, the breach was ſo large, that there was no difficulty to enter it, and if wee had not erected a rampire or Countermure, fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſupported with timber, which the demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed houſes afforded, wee could not well have held it.</p>
            <p>The Artillery did no great damage to the wall, but rather to the Parapelts, on which the Battery was made in foure places, by innumerable Cannon ſhot, for there paſſed not a day naturall (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of 24 houres) wherein there were not accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1200, and the quantity of the great ſhot was ſuch, that (as the French obſerved) our Artillery was cloyed thereby, and could not be of any uſe to us, without new carriages.</p>
            <p>We had not beene ſo well aſſured of the place, had wee not beene aſſiſted by the Women, who were very cheerefull, ſome helping to dig in our trenches, others charging our Muſquets with great expedition, and bringing powder and ſhot in their
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:25768:60"/>lapps, that we might diſcharge the oftner, others apparrelling themſelves in the habits of men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the courage to skirmiſh with the enemy, whereſoever they ſhould give the aſſault, with greateſt fury, which we daily expected.</p>
            <p>It is affirmed that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Veles</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred a noble Lady in that poſture with her Muſquet, reſt, and white ſafeguard: who ſeeing him ſaid, let not your excellency marvell, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day ſince the ſiege, I have diſcharged two Muſquets, but this day more: And immediately ſhe diſcharged very gracefully, his excellency ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a reſpective remonſtrance of Honour to her fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine valour.</p>
            <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Fonteraby</hi> were ſo feeble, that it was an extraordinary griefe to behold: for their houſes for the moſt part were battered, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable for uſe or ſhelter: and they had not above two Quintals of powder, having waſted 800. The French gained many places in <hi>Reutoria,</hi> where onely were remaining, but 15 houſes.</p>
            <p>The Covent of <hi>Monkes</hi> were halfe burnt, ours ſcarce received any loſſe at all, before ſome of the Fathers of <hi>Bayona</hi> came thither: and when wee thought we had loſt all, God was pleaſed to offer us a meanes of reſtitution, and by the great piety and affectionate devotion, wherewith the Lord Admirall was pleaſed to honour us, having vowed to reedifie and repair all the dammages of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie cauſed by deſtruction of the Buildings; I preſented my ſelfe to give thankes to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:25768:61"/>who aſſured me that he had acquainted his Catholique Majeſty (whom God preſerve) therewith, and hath wrote earneſtly to the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke, praying that it might be put to his account, to repaire the dammage which the <hi>Capuchins</hi> had received; whereof his Majeſty tooke notice, and over and beſides, undertooke to provide ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations, which were wanting to the ſaid Fathers, and we owe this noble Prince an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meaſure of reſpect, for his favour towards a priſoner of our habit, which was amongſt the French: for whom the Prince ſent his Trumpetter to <hi>Bayon,</hi> accompanied with two Fathers of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: The father <hi>Francis Barnard</hi> of <hi>Pompelona,</hi> the Father <hi>Iuan</hi> of <hi>Loarra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre this <hi>Capuchin,</hi> who <hi>de facto</hi> relateth a truth, though he may erre perhaps in the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, imputing that to feare, which was in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability occaſioned by faction, as may bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Conſequents, which are to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in our next Relation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London Printed for Na. Butter,</hi> and <hi>N. Bourne.</hi> Feb. 6. 1639.</p>
            <p>With Priviledge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25768:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
